Wave
Wave
technology
technology
Message
Message
General Zhu is a very important political scientist
朱將者是非常重要的政治學者
Professor Wu Yushan, I don't think I need a special introduction
吳昱山教授我想不需要我特別介紹
You can sometimes see him in the newspapers
各位有時候也可以在報紙上看到他
Comments on ten moves
對十舉的評論
But I still want to briefly introduce his resume
但是我還是要稍微簡單介紹一下他的簡歷
Dr Wu is a 1976 graduate of Jianguo Middle School
吳博士是1976年畢業建國中學
I think many of you recall the time in 1970
我想各位很多都回憶起1970年的時候
The international situation in Taiwan at that time
那時候台灣的國際局勢
When official changes are dramatic
正式變化非常厲害的時候
The international situation was already very unfavorable to the Republic of China at that time
國際局勢對中華民國當時已經有很多不利的局面
So at that time, Dr. Wu was admitted to the Political Science Department of National Taiwan University for the first time.
所以當時吳博士就以第一次考進台大政治系
Hope to make a difference to reality
希望對現實有所作為
Four years later he graduated first
四年以後他以第一名畢業
In fact, he graduated first in all of them.
事實上他全部都是以第一名畢業
He graduated first from all of this
他從這個全部都是以第一名畢業
Then what
然後呢
In order to understand the other side and international communism, I am admitted to politics
為了瞭解對岸跟國際共產主義來考入政治
Also graduated first in 1980
在1980年也是以第一名畢業
Applying for entry after two years of benefits
在福利兩年後申請進入
Department of Political Science, University of California, Berkeley
美國加州伯克萊大學的政治系
Then his question was
然後他的提問是
Nominalist State and Property Rights
命名主義國家與財產權
Mutual Ping is the Study of Economic Reform in Mainland China
互平是中國大陸經濟改革的研究
Also received in 1992
在1992年也獲得
American Political Science Association's Best Ph.D. Player
美國政治學會最佳的博士玩家
After he came back, he worked in the Department of Political Science, National Taiwan University.
回來以後他就在台大政治系
Director of Intervention Affairs from Associate Professor
從副教授教授干預事主任
Then in 2006 to Zhongyuan Institute
然後在2006年到中原院
director of political science empowerment
擔任政治學授權處的主任
Currently a designated salesperson and director
現在是特定營業人兼所長
Dr. Lin got a lot of lives
林博士獲得了的命非常之多
He has won national science awards three times
他曾經三次國科學級出獎
National Taiwan University Mobile Teaching Award
台大手機教學級出獎
Ministry of Education Academic Award
教育部學術獎
Twice National Academy of Sciences Award
兩次國科科科學院就獎
And outstanding specific rescuers
還有傑出特定營救人
And he also served as a member of the National Science and Technology Department
而且他也在國科科擔任過
Top Ph.D. players named in political science
政治學名最重要的博士玩家
Is the shaper of political science
就是政治學門的造型人
His field of study includes the Socialist State
他的研究領域包括社會主義國家
Political and Economic Transformation Democratization and Constitutional Design
政治與經濟轉型 民主化與憲政設計
Cross-strait relations and international theory
兩岸關係跟國際理論
And lead Taiwan's semi-funded research
而且領導台灣的半種有資研究
Theoreticalization of research on cross-strait relations
跟代表兩岸關係研究之理論化
Fifteen books in English written and edited by him
他著作跟編寫的十五本英文專書
Books in Chinese and English More than 100 journals and book papers
中英文專書 百餘篇期刊跟專書論文
Here I should introduce Director Wu
這裡我應該介紹吳所長
Director Wu does not need to read the documents
吳所長不需要看文件
Because I know all too well about his whole academics and science too
因為我對他的整個學術和科學也太了解
and adore
而且非常的崇拜
When I was in Guoke local culture modeling people
我在國科當地學問造型人的時候
I happen to be the director of the humanities department
我正好是當任人文處的處長
So I have a lot of work with him
所以我跟他有很多的工作上
There are also academic professors
還有學問上的教授
I also admire his research very much.
對他的研究也非常之佩服
The topic he is going to talk about today
他今天要講的這個題目
I was eating just now
我剛剛也在吃飯的時候
Exchange your relics with Director Wu
跟吳所長交換你的遺跡
I think it's an interesting topic
我覺得這是很有意思的題目
And it's good for impromptu
而且很有利即興
i don't know how you guys are doing
我不知道各位怎麼樣
I always think inside
我常常老在裡面以為
Wow, political development should be like this today
哇 政治發展要今天這樣
It's almost there. The next game hasn't progressed yet.
差不多了 下一局還沒怎麼發展呢
10 years later
結果再過10年
Politics still has a new round
政治還是有新的一局產生
will affect the strength
對實力會有影響
Humans probably do
人類大概本事就是
Talk about to the extent
話也大概話到程度
Good and good, to the extent of the day
好有好 到日程度
It will take 10 years for you to have a new situation
你要過10年又有新的形勢出來
Then Secretary Wu will tell you today that history has not ended
那吳書長今天就告訴你歷史沒有結束
It's not like Heige said
不像黑哥講的
The history of NLP history does not end
那NLP史 歷史沒有結束
meaning keeps changing
意思一直在變
So the political situation in Taiwan
所以台灣的政治的形勢
Line of entry with competitive style
跟競爭的方式的著線
has been changing
一直在轉變
what's next
下一步要怎麼樣
we listen now
我們現在聽
A Discussion by Secretary Wu of the Institute of Political Science
政治所的吳書長的高論
you applause
你掌聲歡迎
Thank you Vice President Wang
謝謝王副院長
Also glad to have today
也很高興今天有
so many listeners
這麼多的聽眾
interested in this topic
對於這個題目是有興趣的
then i
那我
I think the way I'm going to talk about this today
我想我今天講這個的方法呢
On the one hand, it is based on my observation of some theories on this topic
一方面是根據我對這個議題的一些學理的觀察
On the one hand, I want to connect this issue with those around us.
一方面我又想把這個議題跟我們周遭的
This political phenomenon that everyone has personally experienced is combined
大家親身感觸過的這種政治的現象結合在一起
I'll try my best
我就盡量試試看
Then I hope everyone can put forward your views and this question
那也希望大家能夠提出您的看法跟這個問題
When this person talks about a paragraph, let's discuss it together
這個人講到一個段落的時候大家一起來討論
The topic I want to talk about today is
我今天所要講的題目是
From identity to economy
從認同到經濟
It is the axis transformation of Taiwan's political competition
就是台灣政治競爭的軸線轉換
Before I start, let me ask you to look at the two sets of pictures
在開始之前我先請大家看兩組圖
then i won't say much
那我不多說什麼
When you look at this picture
大家看這個圖的時候呢
Maybe it will provide some of your memories and some feelings
可能就會供起一些你的記憶跟一些感覺
Because we have brought meaning from these two sets of pictures, let’s talk about
因為我們從這兩組圖所帶給了意義再來往下講
Let's see it as a melting point of water
我們先看成水點融化的事情
These are all things that happened to everyone
這些都是大家在進一當中發生過的事情
The central government and Taipei City have different views on this matter
這個事情上人中央跟台北市的看法是不一樣的
I remember this scene
這個景象來我都記得
feel this cartoon
感覺這個漫畫
take this comic
把這段漫畫
It turns out that the same direction of President Chiang
原來這個蔣總統的同向
All concentrated in the mainland of Taoyuan
都集中到桃園的大陸
Daxi went
大西去了
if someone has visited
如果有人去參觀過的
All kinds of fellow countrymen are there
各式各樣的同鄉都在那邊
This is a series of induced movements
這是一連串的感應的運動
medium oil
中油啊
ship
中船啊
In fact, when everyone was flat
其實大家扁的那個時候
we had a time
我們曾經有段時間
That stamp is called Taiwan stamp
那個郵票是叫台灣郵票
Later Ma Ying-jeou came up
後來馬英九上來的
It became the stamp of the Republic of China again
又變成中華民國郵票
It's a huge movement
這是一個很波瀾壯闊的運動
ok then we all have to look down now
好,那我們現在都要往下看
Ma Ying-jeou period
馬英九時期
since 2008
就是從2008年以後
Fumao, there was a debate and now it's cancelled.
福茂,本來有個辯論現在取消了
But of course it's still very controversial
但現在當然還是爭議很大
Some people even think that the fight between the two gentlemen Ma and Wang has something to do with this
甚至有人還認為馬王兩位先生的彼此之間的過招都跟這個有關係
Dismantle the earth today, tear down the government tomorrow
今天拆大土,明天拆政府
This catchphrase reminds everyone
大土都想起來的一個這個口號
This is the electric palm
這是油電雙掌
at the end of last year
去年年底的時候
This wave of military education
軍工教的這一波
Of course, it's also related to my husband.
當然也跟老公的這個連帶
earn tax together
一起掙手稅
down a minister
下來一位部長
The report is now almost dead
報告現在幾乎可以說無疾而終了
good
好
Okay, these two sets of pictures
好 這兩組圖
Here's to the two presidents
給大家這兩位總統的這個
era period
時代時期
different social controversies
不同的社會爭議
what did we see
我們看到了什麼東西
Let's start with these two sets of graphs
我們從這兩組圖開始往下講
we look at any society
我們看任何一個社會
there is a way to understand it
有一個方法去了解它
That's where Clubwich is
就是Clubwich 是在什麼地方
Basically we can divide into three types
基本上我們可以分成有三種
a prematter
一個叫前物質
one is matter and one is post matter
一個是物質 一個後物質
In fact, how much is according to the new formula
其實多少是按照新方的
differentiated by historical development
歷史發展來做區分的
The former material Primitillist speaks of
前物質Primitillist 講的是
ethnic group religion
族群 宗教
It's very basic, very traditional
那是很基本的 很傳統的
on the industrial side no
在工業的那邊沒有
before coming
來到以前就有的
matter left and right
物質 左跟右
So let's go into more detail
所以我們還是比較更詳細的講
Basically because after the revolution came
基本上就是 因為革命來了以後
modern society
產生了現代社會
In modern society, it is easy to divide into labor and capital
在現代社會裡頭容易分成勞資
then this country
那麼就這個國家
in this economy
在這個經濟當中
what kind of position
又佔什麼樣的一個地位
it actively intervenes
它要積極地介入
Because the market is under-allocated
因為市場的分配是不足的
Not even allowing the market to be replaced
甚至於又不讓取代市場
this is socialism
這個是社會主義
or should it basically
還是說它基本上應該
respect all property
尊重所有財產
Then this Qing Liao robbed the rich
然後這個清遼劫富
Let the market do its thing
讓市場去發生它的力量
To create wealth for everyone
去替大家創造才富
These two different views are divided into left and right
這兩種不同的看法就分成左右
The Age of the Afterlife
後遇者的時代
It's the environment, for example, the Lu Party
就是環境比方說陸黨
or gender politics and so on
或者說性別政治等等
In the west we find
在西方我們發現
It is dominated by material differences
它是以物質的分歧為主的
Here comes the industrial revolution
就工業革命來啦
Positive differentiation occurs
積極分化產生啦
different actors then have their own interests
然後不同行為者有它自己的利益
The biggest controversy is what I just said
最大的爭議就是剛剛講的
The role of the state in economic life
國家在經濟生活中扮演的角色
The so-called leftists mean that the state wants to intervene
所謂左也者就是國家要介入
That is to say, it is better for the state to intervene less
那右就是說國家最好少介入
this in the present west
這個在現在的西方
still the main axis of competition
還是主要競爭的主軸
It's interesting
這很有趣
in western countries
在西方的國家當中
Almost always make a distinction between left and right
幾乎都是以左右做區別
so like in america
所以像在美國
it compares to the left
它比較左
Of course, the United States as a whole is relatively right.
當然美國整個算是比較右
But it is relatively left
不過它相對來講比較左的
is the Democratic Party
是民主黨
right is republican
右邊是共和黨
Britain is more left
英國來講比較左的
Is the public party
是公黨
Paulista on the right
右邊是保走黨
There's a Lipdance over here
這邊有一個Lipdance
That right said it was in Germany
那右說在德國的
Just had a general election, right?
剛剛舉行大選對不對
To the left are the Social Democrats
比較左邊的是社會民主黨
right
對
The right might be the Christian Democrats
右邊可能就是基督教民主黨
this
這個
have such competing spindles
都有這樣的競爭的主軸
Political parties divide along this society
政黨沿著這個社會分歧
Collecting position
採取立場
If the party
如果說這個政黨
words that ignore major social divides
忽略主要的社會分歧的話
its political influence will be weakened
它的政治影響力就會消弱
Now everyone is arguing about one thing
現在大家都在爭執一個東西
then i jumped out
然後我突然跳出來
make a claim
做一個主張
no one knows what i'm doing
沒有人知道我在幹什麼
They will quarrel with him today
今天來他們就吵他的
Your political influence is gone
你的政治的影響力就沒有了
in western countries
在西方國家中
Prominence of material divergence
物質分歧的突出性
is the majority party
是大多數的政黨
take left and right positions
都要採取左右的立場
Of course in some cases
當然在一些情況下
can still see
還是可以看到
pre-substance divergence
前物質的分歧
for example
比方說
will be held in 2014
2014年就要舉行
Is it from the UK
是不是要從英國的
It should be said United Kingdom
應該說是United Kingdom
independent scotland
獨立出去的蘇格蘭
for example
比方說
in mainland spain to catalonia
在西班牙大陸到卡特羅尼亞
It's from Barcelona
就是巴斯羅納這邊
it is strongly independent
它是有很強的獨立的
this tendency
這種傾向
Kerbac in Canada
克巴克在加拿大
There has always been such a trend
一直有這樣的一個趨勢
France also has
法國也有
But basically
不過基本上來說
those are the few main ones
那些是少數主要的
still around
還是左右
But in selfish democracies
可是在私心民主國家中
This is not the case anymore
情形就不是這個樣子了
Because of the social divisions in many of these countries
因為很多這種國家的社會分歧
it may be latent
它可能是潛物之性的
good
好
if there is
如果說有
specific social divisions
特定的社會分歧
then you will have
那你就會有
Certainly the party system
一定的這個政黨的體系
with it
伴隨著它
Your social divide on the left
你左路的社會分歧
You'll be a party of the left and the right
你就會左派右派的政黨
if say your
如果說你的
society has experienced some
社會經歷了一些
major development
重大的發展
it may change
它有可能會改變
One even
一體甚至於
bring out new social divisions
帶出新的社會分歧
Social divisions may change
社會分歧可能會變的
no
不是
never change
永遠一成不變
So the new social pit period
所以新的社會坑期
May replace old divergence
可能會取代舊的分歧
or the old one here
或者是說舊的在這裡
Separate the symphony after the new one appears
新的出現以後分開交響
then exist together
然後一起都存在
Political parties have to chase votes, right?
政黨必須要追求選票對不對
so he has to pay close attention
所以他就要密切注意
Is there a new topic
是不是有新的議題
Is there a new disagreement
是不是有新的分歧
So it appeared
於是就出現了
Party redirection through elections
透過選舉帶來的政黨重新導向
his
他的
The reason why his political party will follow the divide
他之所以政黨會跟著分歧
Going because he wants votes
走是因為他要選票
Then the difference is decided
那這個分歧就決定了
What is the society most concerned about
這個社會最關切的是什麼
so you have to follow him around
所以你必須要跟著他來轉
let me give you an example
我舉個例子來講
In the UK the Conservative Party is called Toy
在英國的保守黨叫Toy
Historically he was a royalist
歷史上他是保皇黨
Of course it is impossible to imagine now
當然現在不可能想像說
there will be a party in england
在英國會出現一個黨
He asserted that the king's right is still the greatest
他主張國王的權利還是最大的
This Toy has become a white-handed political party
這個Toy就變成了白手主義的政黨
so he has to follow this
所以他必須跟著這個
Time changes with the development of this history
時間跟著這個歷史的發展來轉變
So social divisions change
所以社會分歧變了
Political parties follow it
政治政黨跟著它變
So a social divide turns into a new political divide
因而社會分歧就演變成一個新的政治分歧
Let's take a closer look at how this process came about.
我們再仔細看一下這個過程是怎麼產生的
Do you think some of the political parties are more innovative?
你覺得政黨當中有一些比較有創新能力
it adjusts its position
它會調整自己的立場
then it wins the election
然後它就在選舉當中獲勝
why ? because new differences have arisen
為什麼?因為有新的分歧產生了
Laggards will be under strong pressure
落後者就會受到強大的壓力
he also has to adjust
他也必須要調整
Because someone has changed
因為前面已經有人變了
you have to change
你也要跟著變
no way to adjust
沒有辦法調整的
will lose votes
就會丟掉選票
Even the party is gone
甚至這個黨就不見了
It's a thief
就是物盡天賊
fit for party survival
適合的政黨生存
Everyone knows that I am based on what Darwin said in biology.
大家知道我這是根據生物學裡面的達爾文的講法來的
It's a thief
就是物盡天賊
fit survival
適合生存
the party
派對
can have several results
可以有幾個結果
One is the original political party is still maintained
一個是原來的政黨還是維持的
But the party has actually changed
但是這個政黨實質改變了
It's as if the Royalists in England have now become the Conservatives
就好像英國的保皇黨現在變成了保守黨
So we see that these parties are still competing on the table
所以我們看到台面上還是這些政黨在競爭
But it's really a new issue
但其實它真的已經是一個新的議題
new differences
新的分歧
Or there is a new political party
或者是說有新的政黨起來
replaced the old party
取代了舊的政黨
so let me say something first
所以我先講一句吧
What we see today is like what Vice President Wang just mentioned
我們今天所看到的就像剛剛王副院長所提的
what we see now
我們現在所看到的
profit blue profit
利盈藍盈
Kuomintang Democratic Progressive Party
國民黨民進黨
Then they argue about something
然後他們吵個東西
then we feel
然後我們覺得
Wow, it's been like this for so many years
哇 多少年都是這個樣子
nothing
沒有的事
Social divides can change
社會分歧是可能變的
And when social divisions change
而當社會分歧變的時候
Political parties must follow suit
政黨必須要隨車來變
otherwise
不然的話
he might disappear
他就可能會消失
die out
消亡
ok then let's look down
好 那我們往下看
What is Taiwan like?
台灣究竟是怎樣呢
In the 1980s, Morgan's early nineties
在1980年代 莫根九年代初的時候
Taiwan's democracy
台灣民主發任
There are two social divides
有兩種社會的分歧
competing with each other
在相互競爭
I remember very clearly
我記得好清楚
At that time, I happened to be from this
那個時候剛好我從這個
Desu Xuele
差不多要拿到德塑學樂
When preparing to return to Taiwan
要準備回台灣來的時候
Because then I'll keep an eye on it
因為那我再關注看看
Taiwan's democracy has only just begun to emerge
那台灣的民主才剛剛開始出現
What kind of democracy will people treat you
人家會對你什麼樣的民主
Will there be class differences?
人家會出現階級分歧嗎
Western countries are like this
西方國家都是這個樣子
and leftists and rightists
還有左派右派
There will also be leftists and rightists here in Taiwan
台灣人這裡也會出現左派右派
Then why is there such a thing
那為什麼會有這樣的東西
because it makes sense
因為滿有道理
Because the Kuomintang has been pursuing the pursuit of excellence in industry and commerce for many years
因為國民黨長年追求是精進工商業
Economic Development Policy Based on Growth
以成長為保向的經濟發展政策
At the same time trade unions are suppressed
同時工會是被壓制的
we call this
我們稱這個叫做
developed capitalist countries
資本主義發展國家
Captive Developmental State
Captive Developmental State
So like this come more up
所以這樣的話來更多的起來
you now have political power
你現在有了政治權力了
Yes, during that time we saw
沒錯,在那段時間我們看到
sport with some features
有一些功能的運動
i was studying in berkland
我那時候在柏克蘭念書
I found that there are many people who do functions
我發現有好多做功能的人
went to berkland to give a speech
跑到柏克蘭做演講
I go to listen to every game
每一場我都跑去聽
do you remember
大家記得嗎
At that time, the disciples also had a very powerful
那個時候的門民還有一個很厲害的
this circular demonstration
這個圓形示威
and burned something
還燒了一些東西
Then opposed the policy at the time
然後反對這個當時的政策
democracy is coming
民主制度來了
All kinds of social voices have risen
各種社會聲音都起來了
Will this power come out?
是不是這個力量會出來呢
or
或者是
Subgroup-Based Identity Analysis
以次族群為基礎的認同分析
Subgroup sub-asnik
次族群 sub-asnik
because usually we don't think
是因為通常我們不認為
Han people in Taiwan
在台灣的漢人吧
Have a way with each other asnik
彼此之間有道 asnik
such a difference
這樣的差別
but it does make a difference
但是它確實有差別
Usually called sub-asnik
通常打叫做 sub-asnik
In Taiwan, we will talk about provincial conflicts
在台灣就會講省級衝突
is it that thing
是不是那個東西
Because the Democratic Party has always emphasized
因為民黨一直強調
It is the resistance of the Chinese nation
是中華民族阻力
outside the party
那黨外
what is emphasized
強調的是什麼
Taiwan's Subjective Consciousness
台灣的主體意識
this is also a conflict
這也是一個衝突
So when you democratize
所以當你民主化了
Many things were suppressed
本來很多東西都壓制住
now democratized
現在民主化了
So what will emerge
那麼會浮現的是什麼樣的
a social divide
一個社會分歧呢
We found that as a result of later development
我們發現後來發展的結果
Identity politics trumps class and distribution
認同政治壓倒了階級跟分配
over twenty years
成為二十多年來
The Axis of Taiwan's Political Competition
台灣政治競爭的主軸
from the 1990s to the 2000s
就是在九零年代一直到兩千年代
A tacit understanding until the 2000s
一直到兩千年代的默契
it's all like this
都是這個樣子
Taiwan is a very interesting phenomenon
台灣是非常有趣的現象
Because people are people in Taiwan politics
因為人就台灣政治的人
can feel
都可以感覺到
we are not so easy
我們不是那麼容易
To talk to the Western democratic system
去跟西方的民主制度而對話
why? because they are left and right
為什麼?因為他們是左右
we are agree
我們是認同
You know what the UK says about identity
你知道英國去講什麼認同
Of course Scotland can have these
當然蘇格蘭可以有這些
Axis of Basic Political Competition
基本的政治競爭的主軸
not agreeing with this phenomenon
不是在認同這根現象
America is the same
美國也是一樣
But we are agreeing
可是我們是在認同上面
we talk less
我們反而少講
class
階級
So I agree with Duxiu
所以認同讀秀
Absence of left and right
左右缺位
No Influential Leftist Party Emerged in Taiwan
在台灣沒有出現有影響力的左派政黨
who are we
我們各位是誰
do we have a communist party
我們有共產黨嗎
Yes, I have
有啊
We can often see a red flag on the street
我們在街上常常可以看到有插個紅旗
and then there in the fifties
然後在那裡那個五零年代
That song is quite majestic
那個歌曲還蠻雄壯的那個
all the way past
一路過去
no one knows what he sings
沒有人知道他唱的是什麼
Then the red flag is waving
然後就紅旗招展
that's all
就這樣
we have the labor party
我們有工黨啊
That's not really a leftist party either.
那個也不是真的左派政黨
in our congress
在我們的國會裡頭
no real leftist parties
就沒有真的左派政黨
Opposition to the KMT
反對國民黨的黨外
later became the Democratic Party
後來變成民進黨
he didn't adopt the platform of a party of the left
他並沒有採取左派政黨的政綱
we don't have any major political parties
我們沒有任何主要的政黨
group as socialism
組當社會主義
deep group socialism
深組當社會主義
by western standards
以西方的標準來看
Taiwan's main political parties are left and right in ideology
台灣的主要政黨在左右的意識形態
right-handed on the spectrum
光譜上都是偏右的
but our right
但是我們的右派
no ideological claims
也沒有意識形態的主張
let me give you an example
我舉個例子來講
private property
在美國認為私有財產
Property-wise is a very important thing
Property-wise是非常重要的一個東西
is extremely sacred
是極為神聖
we don't feel that way either
我們也沒有這個感覺
It's basically a matter of left and right
基本上就是左右的議題
Disagreement in Taiwan
跟分歧在台灣
That is undetdeveloped
那是undetdeveloped
we don't have that language
我們沒有那種語言
we don't have that concept
我們沒有那種概念
we don't have that awareness
我們沒有那個意識
isn't it good
是不是很好呢
seems to be good
好像是不錯
but we replace it with something else
但是我們用另外一個東西取代
we have two bourgeois parties
我們有兩個資產階級的政黨
KMT strengthens ties with factories
國民黨強化跟工廠界的關係
yes
沒錯
The DPP also has its own donors and money veins
民進黨也有自己的金主跟錢脈
electoral competition brings
選舉競爭帶來了
Huge need for political cash
巨大的政治現金的需求
underdeveloped trade unions
而低度發展的工會
no way to party
沒有辦法對政黨
provide financial assistance
提供財政意助
We see election competition costs money
我們看選舉競爭都要花錢
right
對不對
where does the money come from
錢從哪裡來
Of course the money comes from the rich
錢當然從有錢人來
so it looks like
所以看起來
Big business of course
當然就是大企業
bourgeoisie to prop
資產階級來支柱
But if you have a
可是如果你有一個
words of a strong union
強大的工會的話
trade unions can be held accountable
工會是可以以責任的
his own strength to support the party
他自己的力量去支持政黨
I think it's good
我覺得很好的就是
because it's happening now
因為現在正在發生
british labor party
英國的工黨
In the long run, we will go together with the trade union
長起來講跟工會是走在一起的
why
為什麼呢
Because of the British trade unions
因為英國工會
the membership they paid
他們所繳交的會員
Fees automatically become a source of funding for the Labor Party
費自動地就變成工黨的資金來源
Now this represents
現在這個代表就是
british labor party leader
英國的工黨領袖
I want to change the country and cut this off
想要改國把這個切掉
many people are shocked
很多人都大驚失
So if you do this
所以這樣搞的話
So where does our Labor Party get its money from?
那麼我們工黨的錢從哪裡來
It is not conceivable at least so far
根本可以想像到至少到目前為止
If the Labor Party, the Labor Party
如果說勞動黨、工黨
its source of funding
它的資金來源
A big part comes from joining the union
好大一邊是來自於參加工會的
money donated by people
人所捐的錢
dues paid
所付的會費的話
Of course it has to reflect the interests of workers
當然它要反映工人的利益
Right
對吧
But our trade union is very naive
可是我們工會發展得很幼稚
Because of course there is no union like that
因為當然沒有那樣的工會
I don't have that kind of wealth
也沒有那樣的財源
So when this party is competing
所以當這個政黨在競爭的時候
As long as you have money, you can suppress it with both sides
所要有錢的,你跟兩邊壓住
so it produces
所以就產生
There is also a lack of control over political cash
對於政治現金也缺乏管制
The business community has a strong lobbying industry
工商界有強大的遊說業
I think we have six business products, right?
我認為我們有六大工商產品對不對
Type of work, type of business, industrial and commercial cooperation, industrial cooperation
工種、商種、工商協進、工業協進
small business
從小企業
electricity electricity
電電電
One is better than the other
一個比一個厲害
when you need the funds
你需要這個資金的時候
You must ask them for help
你必然需要求助你他們
Business and industry are closely related to the brain
工商有些跟大腦之間關係非常密切
Let's play golf together, right?
一起打高爾夫嘛,對吧
So social welfare increases
所以社會福利之處增加
like
好像
This is an unreasonable taste
這個是不大原則的味道
But in fact it does not reflect the politics of ruthlessness
但其實並非反應肉統政治
or you are
不然你就是
You also have to give some benefits to your constituency
你也要給你自己選區點利益
I also want to give some benefits to my constituency
我也要給我選區點利益
so i also
所以我也
Help you to transfer part of the money to your constituency
幫你能夠把一部分的錢跟你的選區
You also let me define where there are some funding places
你也讓我定義有一些地方的經費之處
Then I don't know where the money will go
然後這個錢到個地方去也不知道
What method is used to send it out?
是用一個什麼方式給發掉
Handicrafts in some places
常常一些地方的手藝工程
what road construction
什麼道路建築
what to do
什麼做的
Flooding with hand power
有攤掉手力的淹水
so
這樣
So actually two bourgeois parties
所以其實是兩個資產階級政黨
it has a reason
它有原因
Because of the sustained high-speed economic development in the past
因為是過去持續的高速經濟發展
because our society moves
因為我們社會移動
The ratings of social mobility are very high
社會流動這個收視活動非常地高
Our education has a strong equalizing effect
我們教育有很強的平等化的效果
This makes your
這樣的話就使得你的這個
The structure of this class is highly mobile
這個階級的結構是具有高度流動性
It is no longer easy to generate economic awareness
已經不容易產生經濟意識
Your parents may actually be third-level reviewers.
你可能父母其實是三級評戶
And you have become our lawyer
而你呢已經變成是對我們的律師
Where is your class consciousness?
那你的階級意識是哪邊
Bayi's incomplete class consciousness
巴依不全的階級意識
It is an industry dominated by small and medium-sized enterprises
而是中小企業為主的產業
it turned out to be interesting
結果這很有意思
Because Taiwan is very different from South Korea and Japan
因為台灣跟韓國跟日本大大的不一樣
South Korea is big business
韓國是大企業
Japan can have a dual economy
日本能有兩元經濟
There are large enterprises and small and medium enterprises
有大企業同時有中小企業
Taiwan is dominated by small and medium-sized enterprises
台灣是以中小企業為主
Taiwan's big companies don't look big in the world
台灣的大企業在世界上看起來都不大
Foxconn exception
富士康例外
Therefore, the adverse impact on the development of the labor movement
所以對勞工運動發展不利的影響
SMEs are particularly hostile to trade unions
中小企業對於工會特別敵視
However, it is easier for trade unions to mobilize and organize in a large enterprise environment.
而工會在一個大企業的環境比較容易動員組織的起來
politics of course repress it
政治當然也壓抑它
So if we compare it with East Asia
所以我們如果跟東亞比較起來的話
You will find that P class politics in East Asian countries in general are not so obvious
你會發現一般來講東亞國家的P級政治都不是那麼明顯
However, compared with Japan and South Korea, the labor movement in Taiwan is especially compared with South Korea.
可是臺灣的勞工運動比起日本跟韓國都特別是跟韓國比較起來
so we the left are absent
所以我們左派是缺位的
that's not left and right that's what we are
那不是左右 那我們是什麼
Political parties do not use left-right policies to win votes
政黨不以左會右的政策來爭取選票
Rather, political competition is waged by the mobilization of opposing identities
而是藉由動員對立的認同來進行政治競爭
what are we looking at now
我們現在看什麼東西
how do we see history
歷史我們怎麼看過去的
what are we going to do now
現在我們要進行什麼情形
what will the future be
未來將來會是什麼
let's look at history first
我們先看歷史
History necessarily involves different times in textbooks
歷史就必然牽涉到教科書不同的時光
Is it a continental or oceanic view of history?
是大陸史觀還是海洋史觀
We think of Taiwan as an extension of the mainland
我們認為台灣是大陸的延伸
In other words, Taiwan is a child of the ocean
或者說台灣是海洋的子女
you are from a continent
你是從一個大陸
Taiwan from Mainland China's point of view
中國大陸的觀點來看台灣
Or regard Taiwan as
還是把台灣看成是
yourself as the center
你自己作為中心
then a marine
然後是一個海洋的
Then there's the influence of the ocean
然後有海洋來的影響力
There is an influence from the mainland
有一個從大陸來的影響力
Is it human or land
是屬人還是屬地
You strongly belong to this group
你強烈是這個族群
It is basically the Chinese nation
它基本上是華夏民族
is from Zhongyuan
是中原來的
is this
是這個呢
still a territory
還是屬地
this is not right
這個對就對不到
Taiwan is right.
台灣這塊地對就對了
different people come
不同的人來
Right
對吧
The Japanese come, the Dutch come, the Chinese come, etc.
日本人來 荷蘭人來 漢人來等等
but the center of your land
但是是你地的中心
what is wrong with this kind of thing
這種事情都是什麼對錯
It depends on what point of view you take
是看你是以哪一個觀點來意義
Just your most hyped Rijiu Garden
就你炒得最厲害的日據園
A real point in the middle of Rijiu Garden
日據園這個中間的一個真點
Is it Japanese data?
是日據嗎
what does japan mean
日據的意思是表示什麼
It's unreasonable for the Japanese to call you
日本人來叫你這就不合理
don't give him legitimacy
不要給他合法性
why not give him legitimacy
為什麼不給他合法性
because of this place
因為這塊地方
It is harmful to the Chinese people and the Chinese people
是害人的 中國人的 華夏人民的
so it's not legal for him to come
所以他來這是不合法
Turning to this point of view of the Republic of China
轉轉中華民國的這個觀點來的
expected
預計呢
It can also be said that the rule itself
也可以說這個治的本身
have a good meaning
有一點好的意思
or at least you can put him
或者至少你可以把他把
cleanup
清理 日治
different times anyway
反正不同的時期
Some from here, some from there
有這裡來的 有那裡來的
There are those from the north and those from the west.
有北邊來的 有西邊來的都有
this is the middle period
這是中間的一個時期
value-neutral
所以認為是價值中立
but value neutral
但是價值中立當中
In fact, all the rulers
其實已經把所有的統治者
relativized
相對化了
Because he actually has two different views
因為他其實有兩種不同的觀點
What he reflects is the view of continental and oceanic history
他反應的就是大陸跟海洋史觀
Humanism is not the same as territorialism
屬人跟屬地主義是不一樣的
now how do we see now
現在 我們怎麼看現在
is to say the official way
是說官方的講法
we are a divided country
我們是一個分裂的國家
We claim sovereignty over the other side
我們對於對岸主張主權
Because we are inferior to him
因為我們是權不及他
He claims sovereignty over us
他裡面對我們主張主權
because of lack of power
因為既權不及
not only us
不止我們
So now it's a divided country
所以現在是處於一個分裂的國家
Is this how you see it?
是這樣看嗎?
still one country
還是一邊一國
There are two views on one side of the country
那一邊一國有兩種看法
one side is
一邊就是
Am I completely unacceptable to the Republic of China?
我對於中華民國是不是完全不接受
Another one is
另外一個就是
ok i accept for now
好 我現在暫時接受
Republic of China
中華民國
But it is the name of Taiwan now
但是它就是現在台灣的名字
We have no legal relationship with the other side
我們跟對岸沒有任何法律上的關係
This Republic of China is Taiwan
這個中華民國就是台灣
what is that?
那是什麼呢?
What are we now?
就是我們現在是什麼?
Different cultural experience also different views
不同的文化經驗也不同的看法
future
未來
Are you going to unify?
對不去統一嗎?
Will it continue to maintain the holy school?
一直維持聖專下去嗎?
Prove Taiwan's independence
要台灣證明獨立
Are you in Jianguo?
置身建國嗎?
different people have different opinions
不同的人也有不同的看法
Aren't we a fun place?
我們是不是很有趣的地方?
We are very basic with these
我們對於這些很基本
for many countries
對於很多國家來講
It's a natural thing to do
這是很自然的事情的東西
we disagree
我們看法是不一致的
Because you agree that nature is different
因為你們認同自然不同
the identity, if it is the main social divide
這個認同,如果它是主要的社會分歧
The main axis of our political competition is of course different
我們政治競爭的主軸,當然就不一樣
Since the late 2000s
從2000年代後期開始
This is an important point and point of view I want to raise
這是我所要提出來的一個重點跟看法
Because we've been on this identification
因為我們一直在這個認同上面
argued for a long time
爭執了很長的時間
this is almost 20 years old
這個幾乎有20年
It is the front half of the inner main picture we just looked at
就是我們剛剛看的那個內主圖的前面一半
The main axis of political competition begins to shift, I think it is called paradise shift
政治競爭的主軸開始轉變,我覺得它叫做paradise shift
It's a paradigm shift
這是一個典範轉移
why?
為什麼呢?
Because economic growth has slowed
因為經濟成長已經減緩了
Therefore, people's desire for basic life has increased
所以民眾對於基本生活的淫慮增加了
The era of high growth has entered and will never return
高成長的時代已經進去不復返
But if it's our age
但是如果是在我們這個年齡
It was during the period of economic take-off
就是在經濟起飛那段時間的
We may think that Ah Star capital raised
我們可能會認為阿星資往上調
economic growth
經濟成長
is a natural thing
是自然的事情
But our time was like this
但我們那個時代是這樣
this age
現在這個年齡
young people from different professions
異業出來的年輕人
He doesn't think and feel that way at all.
他完全不是這個看法跟感覺
my daughter complains to me
我的女兒跟我抱怨
His daughter was alive and well
他女兒那時候活得很好
i heard he worked hard
我聽他很辛苦
I heard how to tell him
我聽到怎麼去跟他說
22K right?
22K對不對
and how many years
而且多少年
There is no salary increase at this time
這個時機薪資是沒有增加的
So the situation in that economy is very different
所以那個經濟的情況差別很大
After the age of identity politics has passed
認同政治斷年過度了以後
everyone is tired
大家有疲累了
Identifying with something is deep in your heart
認同一種東西是在你心靈深處
maybe when i was very young
可能是很小的時候
grown up in the family
在家庭當中就已經成長而成
Because I keep picking that thing
因為不斷去挑那個東西
it's very uncomfortable
是搞得很不舒服
third
第三
Wait a minute, I want to talk about this
這個等一下我特別要講
cross-strait relations
兩岸關係
Identity is a bridge between identity and economy
認同是認同跟經濟中間的一個橋樑
Anyway, there are several main reasons
反正有這幾個主要的原因
Axis shift
軸線發生轉變
process first
過程第一個
New social divisions appear to be emerging
新的社會分歧看起來逐漸浮現
the second
第二個
The KMT has changed after losing the election
國民黨在敗選了以後發生改變了
third
第三
The Democratic Progressive Party has also transformed under the pressure of the election
民進黨在選舉的壓力底下也轉型了
Let's take a closer look
我們比較仔細的來看
what am i talking about
我講的究竟是什麼
Let's take a look at the state of the economy
我們來看一下這個經濟的情況
how the economy is doing
經濟進行情形如何
The average economic growth rate in the 1990s was 6.93%
1990年代的經濟成長率平均是6.93%
Everyone at that time
各位那個時候
I saw numbers in the 1990s and felt
在1990年代看過數字覺得
not so good
不怎麼樣
The 1980s were double-digit growth
1980年代是兩位數的成長
2000 to 2007
2000到2007年
satisfy the ruling
滿足執政
During the period when the governance point was in power
對整治點執政的這段時間
From 2007 to 2008, half of them were in power under the KMT
講07年至2008的時候已經有一半是在國民黨執政
At that time it was adjusted to 4.43%
那個時候調到4.43%
KMT slams DPP
國民黨抨擊民進黨
total economy
這個這個總經濟
Of course it only goes up and down
當然它只有上下起伏
it's not average that way
它不平均是這樣
2008 to 2011 or 2012
2008到2011年或12年
These data are sometimes 100 million and sometimes 12
這幾個數據有時是1億有時是12的
adjusted to 3.2%
調到3.2%
what do we hear now
現在我們聽到什麼
Baoer, right?
寶二對不對
Poichi
寶一
Wenwen grew up in the 1980s
在1980年代成長的文文
Have you ever heard of such numbers?
有聽過這種數字嗎
but that's how it is now isn't it
但現在就是這樣不是
Strongly narrate
極力敘述
minimum is 0
最小是0
Maximum is 1
最大是1
it is coming
它是來
measure your income inequality
橫量你的所得收入的不平等的情況
If it is 0, it is the most equal
如果是0的話就是最平等
If it is 1, it is the most unequal
如果是1的話就是最不平等
We see strong narrative
我們看到極力敘述
9.0.317
9.0.317
0.1 to 0.7 years is 0.34
0.1到0.7年是0.34
Then continue to grow to 0.343
然後繼續在增長到0.343
this looks
這個看起來
can't match the feeling
沒有辦法配合感覺
Because it doesn't change much
因為它變動的數值不大
We see why indexing is good
我們看到為什麼要指數好
This is our coefficient for Dabao
這是我們對大寶系數
Dabao coefficient is generally understood by everyone
大寶系數大家比較通常理解
It's the one with the highest income
就是那個所得最高的那個加護
20%
20%
The ratio between the bottom 2%
跟最低的2%中間的比例
most powerful group
最有權的力群
Liqun
跟最沒有權的力群
Its income is worse than the original
它的收入跟原比是差的
how much to add
加多少
good
好
1690s is 5.33
1690年代是5.33
2002 706.03
2002年706.03
2008 to 2011 is 6.19
2008到2011是6.19
keep going up
不斷地在往上升
Compare the above with international
用國際的比較上面
come and see
來看起來的話
compared to Japan
就我們比起日本
Already relatively speaking
已經相對來講
is not equal
是不平等了
South Korea pulls higher than ours
韓國比我們的這個拉得更高
Americanization
美國化
Of course it's more scary
當然就更可怕
because it is more capitalist
因為它更是資本主義
its large island coefficient
它的這個大島系數
if singapore
如果是新加坡
up to 20
可以到20
this number is very large
這個數字是非常大的
but in our case
但我們的情況
is also changing
也是越來越變
Unemployment rate 2.043.7
失業率2.043.7
4.77
4.77
Unemployment is constantly increasing
失業率不斷地在增加
So this graph of the economy
所以這種經濟的圖形
Bottom Natural Member Home
底下很自然的會員家
is the case of an interest rate economy
是利率經濟的情形
so we showed up
所以我們出現了
triple phenomenon
三重現象
growth decline
成長下跌
increase in unemployment
失業率增加
Organizational Allocation Deterioration
組織分配惡化
The triple phenomenon
這三重現象
foundation eroded
基礎受到侵蝕
later for some reason
以後有一些原因
Including we have no way
包括我們已經沒有辦法
Constantly providing new factors of production
不斷地在提供新的生產因素
fully employed
充分就業了
Growth-oriented developmentalism is being challenged
追求成長的發展主義受到挑戰
Because we can't talk about everything on the spot
因為我們現場不能夠都講
just for economic growth
只是要經濟成長
Too many other factors come into play
太多其他的因素會進來
environmental protection
環境保護啊
For example
好比講
I seem to be talking recently
最近好像在講
If you want to demolish a house
如果要拆一個房子的話
under many conditions
必須要很多的條件底下
to be able to look like this
才可以這個樣子
For example around here
比方說這個附近
Is it this ring bottle?
是不是這個環瓶
of course one of them
當然是其中之一
Is there any other remedy?
那有沒有其他的補救的方法
do you have to do this
一定要做這個嗎
if you tear it down
如果你是拆下去的話
what might happen
可能會產生什麼樣的情形
Zhang Jiaofang, right?
張教訪對不對
two people died, right?
死了兩個人是不是
Then today you're going to demolish the house
然後今天你要拆房子
we want to dismantle the government
我們要拆政府
Everyone is very disgusted
大家反感非常的強
because you are actually developmentalist
因為你其實發展主義
They all regard this thing as a major social loss
完全都把這個東西當成是一個重大的社會損失
In such a situation, it is also like this
以這個樣的情形來講也是這樣子
tear down the old street
把舊的一條街拆掉
Because of the road, the straight road came out
因為馬路 筆直的馬路就開出來了
Then some ice pools gradually appeared, right?
然後慢慢出現一些冰子庫對不對
And then came the most amazing ice storage, right?
然後又出現了最牛的冰子庫對不對
He's dead against it, isn't he?
他自死反對 是嗎
Then everyone started to sympathize with him.
然後呢 大家就開始給他同情了
unimaginable here before
在以前這邊不可想像
Of course, the situation in Taiwan is even more like this.
台灣的情況當然走得更是這個樣子
Continuing on independence, there is no way to maintain national security capabilities limited
繼續關於獨立性 沒有辦法維持國安能力受到限制
Or give an example, Li Hongyuan, Minister Li
或舉個例子 李洪源 李部長
He just kept talking
他就這麼繼續關聊
You talk now and you can feel it
你現在講話 你就可以感覺得到
I know what he means
他的意思 我就知道是這個樣子
You don't know, you don't listen to me
你們是不清楚的 你就不聽我的話
Of course, use the stratum to go offline and then flood it.
當然就用地層下線 然後就淹水
Giving you 600 billion is not enough
給你六千億都不夠
Just impolite and promiscuous, right?
就禮盲又濫情 對不對
that's how people are
民眾就是這樣
New year's industrial policy in doubt
新一年的產業政策受到質疑
In the past, the country wanted to develop
以前呢 就是國家要發展
Recently it seems to me
最近好像我看
There I saw Zhang Zhongru's impact made by a NHK Japanese
那裡看到一個NHK日本人做的張中如他的那個撞擊
I just wanted to say how did you get here on a ride?
就想說你騎人這是怎麼過來的
because of industrial policy
因為產業政策
It is how to bring a country in the direction of a specific industry
就是如何把一個國家往特定的產業的方向來帶
The country is going this way
國家往局面往這邊走
This situation of continuing to care for is going this way
這個繼續關愛局面往這邊推展
see clearly
看得很清楚
I know if it's going in any direction
我知道有沒有往哪個方向發展
But now the industrial policy in the new field
可是現在新的領域的產業政策
not so simple situation
不是那麼簡單的局面
biotechnology industry
要讓生技產業
God, how much are you going to spend in the biotech industry?
天啊 生技產業你要花多少錢
How many years to burn money
燒錢燒多少年
I asked a relative in America
我問一個親戚在美國
one of his pharmaceutical factory jobs
他的一個藥廠工作
From the very beginning to the end of his pharmaceutical factory
他這個藥廠從一開始一直到
he left the drug factory
他離開那個藥廠
to develop a drug
就要開發一種藥
he made a lot of money
他賺了很多錢
Their medicine was never developed
他們藥從來沒有開發出來
I'm weird I'm thinking
我就很奇怪 我在想
Will you do it alone?
你一個人會不會做出來
how do you get rich
你怎麼會有錢
just pay yours
就付你的這個
And how did you get so rich yourself?
還有你自己怎麼會那麼有錢
so you have to take a long time
所以你必須要很長的時間
it is possible to create
才有可能去創造出來
This kind of enterprise, the products in this kind of industry
這種企業 這種產業裡頭的產品
Very difficult
很困難
And it is still very controversial
而一直到現在都是有很大的爭議性
Coupled with neoliberal economic policies in power
再加上新自由主義的經濟政策當道
increase the proportion of property income
造成財產所得的比重增加
I want to ask everyone
我想請問各位啊
you or those around you
你或者那你周圍的人
How much of your money comes from new
你所賺的錢有多少是來自於新的
Guys I think all the money you make is from new
各位我認為你賺的所有的錢都是來自新的
you are definitely not a rich man
你絕對不是一個有錢的人
OK really rich people
OK 真正有錢的人
his property
他的財產所得裡頭
The vast majority are not from new
絕大的部分不是來自新的
what is it from
是來自於什麼
his property
他的財產所得
what is his property
他的財產所得是什麼
he is buying that house
他在買那個房子
He bought and sold the house
他房子買了再賣掉
buy again sell
再買了再賣掉
how much in the middle
中間就有多少
he was in joe valley
他在喬谷
He fried a big bone
他炒一個好大的骨頭
Someone jumped in and he let go
有人跳進去他脫手
He said how much he can earn
他就說可以賺多少
That's really coming and going
那個真是一來一去
Sell ​​it compared to your whole life
賣比起你這個一輩子
The money to be earned will be much more
都要賺的錢都要來得多得多
So do we have any restrictions on the housing market now?
所以我們現在對於房市有什麼限制嗎
we have this market price right?
我們有這個市價對不對
But we have announcement restrictions
但是我們有公告限制
now want to change
現在是想要改變
But the main force is very big
但是主力非常大
and then your so-called luxury tax
然後你所謂的奢侈稅
That is, you bought it and sold it quickly
就是你買了很快的賣掉
he deducts tax for you
他給你扣個稅
That's what's been said recently
這就是最近才講出來的事情
Why
為什麼
young people can't stand
年輕人受不了
Your house is hard to find.
你這房子拼他拉往上找
I remember that President Ma used to be like
我記得以前馬總統好像
Did he just come to power or when he actually got elected?
他是剛剛執政還是說他真的進選的時候
I remember hearing a sentence at that time
我記得那個時候聽到一句話
i heard very test
我聽到很測
He said a bottle of millions is not a dream
他說一瓶百萬不是夢
How long will it take the young man to buy it
那年輕人要花多少時間才買得了
But of course, it also represents the continuous understanding of funds
但當然也是代表資金不斷的領悟
full confidence in this society
對這個社會中滿信心
So prices keep going up
所以房價不斷往上走
So under the circumstances of Xinziroom
所以新自如的情況底下
Ami on this piece of property
亞美在財產的這一塊
as much as possible
可以盡量的
Come here as much as you want
這個盡情的來
Through the mechanism of the market
透過市場的機制
Buying and selling machinery wealth
買賣來機具財富
The same is true for the US
美國的情況也是一樣
The deteriorating situation of the income of the United States
美國的這個所得的惡化的這個情況
compared to Taiwan
比起台灣來講
more than anything
是有過之而無不及
so these will
所以這些都會
neoliberalism is relevant
新自由主義是有關聯的
Quantitative economic performance begins
量額經濟表現開始
fade
褪色
Then go to Taiwan
然後過去台灣
no class conflict
沒有階級衝突
a very important reason
一個很重要的原因
It is our continuous high growth
是我們持續高成長
Rapid social mobility and extremely low unemployment
快速的社會流動跟極低的失業率
There is also the distribution of income relative to the military
還有相對軍人的所得分配
In this case
這樣的話
Think about it in this high-speed flow situation
你想想看這種高速流動的情況裡頭
Not easy to generate class consciousness
不容易產生階級意識
right
對不對
But looking forward to the future we can't see
可是沾望未來我們看不到
Prospects for improving economic conditions
經濟狀況改善的前景
So worries about economic life
所以對於經濟生活的憂慮
Of course it will affect the political considerations of the people
當然會影響到民眾的政治考慮
I have no way to grow the past senior
我沒有辦法把過去的高層長
regarded as necessary
當作是視為必然
So the main axis of political competition in Taiwan
所以臺灣的政治競爭的主軸
Impossible not to be in this situation
不可能不在這個情境底下
also affected by some
也受到若干的影響
This is the economic part
這是講經濟的這一塊
Let's talk about a kind of mobilization
再來講動員所造成的一種
the exhaustion
這個 exhaustion
It's been robbed
就是已經歷劫了
already tired
已經倦怠了
When the public is still accustomed to accepting
當民眾還是習以把認同
When seen as a major social divide
視為主要社會分歧的時候
economic factors at that time
那個時候的經濟因素
still no way to become a voter
還是沒有辦法成為選民
I think this is the primary consideration
覺得這首要考量
let me give you an example
我舉個例子來講
in 2001
在2001年的時候
Taiwan has experienced unprecedented secondary growth
臺灣曾經出現過前所未有的副成長
previous oil crises
以前幾次石油危機
We don't have secondary growth
我們都沒有副成長
Back then it was vice 1.65
當年是副1.65
Income distribution is deteriorating rapidly
所得分配快速惡化
At that time, the Kuomintang jumped out and said
當時的國民黨就跳出來說
Wow look what the economy is doing
哇 你看 經濟搞成這個樣子
Attacking the Democratic Progressive Party like this
這個樣子就攻擊民進黨
But voters were not affected by this
可是選民並沒有受到這個影響
Basically in 2004 we had a presidential election
基本上2004年我們舉行了總統大選
March and congressional elections in December
3月還有國會大選12月
maintain the political status quo
也都維持了政治的現狀
This is really the status of the Democratic Progressive Party
這真的民進黨的地位
Nor was it affected by today's performance
也沒有因為今天的表現而受到影響
why is this very important
這個蠻重要的為什麼
Because Taiwan's economy has been growing rapidly in the past
因為台灣過去的經濟一直都快速增長
At that time there was an unprecedented major crisis
在那個時候出現了前所未有的重大危機
But the common people have no rules and the ruling party
可是老百姓並沒有規則與執政黨
In the era of Ah Bian
在阿扁的時代
Almost Every Election Becomes a Consensus Choice
幾乎每一次的選舉都變成一個認同的抉擇
Even when the Democratic Progressive Party's election situation began to decline in 2005
即使民進黨的選情在2005年開始走下坡的時候
President Chen still insists on confronting the KMT on the issues he agrees with
陳總統仍然堅持在認同的議題上跟國民黨對決
Let's take a look at the main picture in the previous paragraph
大家看看前面的那一段的主圖
Too much of this event revolves around periods of identification
太多這個事件圍繞在跟認同相關的時期
It was the big thing at that time
這是那個時候的大勢大非
Now we talk about the big trend and the big wrong has its special meaning
我們現在講大勢大非有它特別的意思
right
對不對
But at that time the tide
但是那個時候的大勢大非
astaffy is there
阿斯大菲是在那裡
There are two levels of antagonism in society
社會上出現兩級對立
Of course many people think
當然有很多人覺得
this time can't stand
這時代受不了
can you stop doing this
能不能不要再這樣搞下去
And cross-strait relations
而兩岸關係
And the relationship between Taiwan and the United States
還有台灣跟美國的關係
also under tension
也處於緊張的狀態當中
of course it looks like this
當然是這個樣子
So recognize the cost of mobilization
所以認同動員的代價
looks full height
看起來是滿高的
Okay, I'm going to talk about the third factor now.
好 我現在再講第三個因素
Cause our axis may transform
造成我們這個軸線可能轉化
On the one hand you care about the economy
一方面你關切經濟
I think this is the most important thing
覺得這是最主要的東西
On the other hand, I agree that there are too many mobilizations
另外一方面認同動員太多了
also feel tired
也覺得很疲累
Between these two there is actually one more
在這兩個之間其實還有一個
This link is cross-strait relations
這個連結 就是兩岸關係
This was in 2008
這是2008年的時候的
A Logical Deduction of the KMT
國民黨的一個邏輯推論
how does it say
它是怎麼說的
Taiwan's economy is slowing down
台灣的經濟正在減速
Distribution becomes an important issue
分配成為重要的問題
At that time, I was talking all day long
那個時候一天到晚在講說
How many people died by burning charcoal
燒炭死多少人
how many people committed suicide or what
又有多少人自殺還是什麼
Now the DPP is saying the same thing about the KMT
現在民進黨就同樣的話在講國民黨
But it was the KMT who started talking about it
不過這話一開始都是國民黨開始
Let's just say the economy is getting worse.
就說經濟狀況變糟糕了
Everyone feels that it is
大家都感覺到確實是
An important reason for Taiwan's economic growth
造成台灣經濟成額的一個重要的原因
is tense to cross-strait relations
是緊張到兩岸關係
Because the relationship between the two sides was really tense at that time.
因為那時候兩岸關係確實緊張
Is investment can not improve
是投資無法改善
if you want to invest
如果你要投資的話
Will you put the money on the missile
請問你會把錢放在飛彈
over there
射出來的那邊
Or the side where the missiles are going to go down?
還是飛彈要射下去的那邊
So Shanghai has a lot of investment
所以上海有很多投資
But you want to invest in Taiwan
可是你要在台灣投資
Wealthy people ask for money
大家有錢人將本求入
Of course I want a political stability
我當然要有一個政治安定
One kind of public opinion is yellow hole
輿論的一種都是黃孔
so you want to improve the economy
所以你要改善經濟
You need to improve cross-strait relations
你就要改善兩岸關係
I can't fight that bowl like it's going to war
我不能跟那碗好像要打仗一樣
To improve cross-strait relations
要改善兩岸關係
From your external standpoint
你對外的這個立場來講
A certain form of One China must come out
某一種形式的一個中國必須要出的來
it's a hollow thought
這是一個挖空心思想
how is a
怎麼樣是一個
We have said in the past they can accept
我們有說的過去他們也能接受
so
所以
If you want something like this
如果你要有這樣的
The so-called Chinese things come out
所謂一個中國的東西出來的話
Nature can't be very strong
自然就不可能非常強的
anthropogenic awareness
人土意識
For example, you can't
譬如說你就不可能
On the one hand there is on the other hand too much to see
一方面就有一方面要太多見了
So the 1992 Consensus reappeared
所以九二共識重新出場
The 1992 Consensus is a term that Su Qi came up with
九二共識是蘇奇想出來的一個名詞
In fact, there was no such term before
其實以前沒有這個名詞
So Lee Teng-hui scolded him
所以李登輝把他罵了
i want to die
我要死之
Everyone is serious, in fact, he thinks
大家認真其實他想的
he is right
是他想的沒有錯
But he did come down to it
但是他確實是歸結了
A so-called consensus at that time
那個時候的一個所謂的共識
What consensus? It's actually very simple
什麼共識呢?其實很簡單
On one side is the People's Republic of China
一邊是中華人民共和國
On one side is the Republic of China
一邊是中華民國
the republic of china says
中華民國說
no republic of china
沒有中華人民共和國
The mainland belongs to the Republic of China
大陸是中華民國的
The People's Republic of China does not have the Republic of China
中華人民共和國沒有中華民國
It has also become the 26th or 27th century
也已經變成26、27世了
is it? ok
是嗎?好
That Taiwan belongs to China
那臺灣是中國的
Both the south side and the north side stand
這兩個南邊北側的立場
How do you come up with something in common?
怎麼樣去想出共同點呢?
is what we think of in common
就是我們想到的共同點
what have in common
什麼共同點?
Everyone thinks I only have one China
人都認為我只有一個中國
so
這樣
that's right
也對啊
in this case
那在這種情況裡頭
The 1992 consensus cannot be stopped
九二共識停不來了
But this horse is also interesting
但這馬也很有意思
He was actually in the 1980s
他其實是在1980年代
out that time
出那個時候
He's in Luyouhui
他就在路友會裡面
he imagined
是他想像
Good God, I always figured it out at that time
好天人那個時候一直想出來
There is this so-called 9 case
有這個所謂的9案
At that time, it was not called Case 9.
那個時候其實不叫9案
Consensus submission of each table
共識交一中各表
come out and write his name
出來書寫給他起的名字
one table
一中各表
That's how I thought about it at that time
那個時候就這樣去想了
But time has changed so long
可是時間已經變了這麼久
By the year 2000
到2000年當年的時候
Taiwanese society is no longer the same
台灣的社會已經不一樣了
you speak a variety of words
你講一中各表的話
Some people may not accept
可能有些人是不能接受的
so he said
所以他就講
This consensus in 1992
1992年的這個共識
one table
就是一中各表
Let's call it the 9-case consensus
我們就把它叫9案共識
Then what
然後呢
I talk about the consensus of 9 cases
我講9案共識
What about the mainland?
大陸呢
As long as there is a consensus on the 9 cases, there will be no war
只要講9案共識就不打仗
As long as you talk about the consensus of 9 cases, you can have investment
只要講9案共識就可以有投資
Just talk about the consensus of 9 cases
只要講9案共識
the economy will get better
經濟就會變好
He just said yes
他就說好啊
just say yes
就說好啊
Because the 9-case consensus did not say
因為這9案共識並沒有說
This is one table
這是一中各表
Because people in Taiwan listen to the mainland a lot
因為台灣的人聽大陸講多了
He has a natural resentment
他心裡有一個自然的反感
Just jump up when you hear one
只要聽到一中就跳起來
But what if you say
可是呢如果你講
The One China we talk about is the 1992 Consensus
一中我們講的一中就是九二共識
Then as long as you hear that one in two is talking about the 1992 Consensus
那只要聽到一中兩個是講九二共識
The 1992 consensus is so good
九二共識那麼好
when you feel good
當你覺得很好
President Ma said that when
馬總統又講那個時候
Dr. Ma Presidential Candidate Says Again
馬醫師總統候選人又說
my eyes are ready
我目睛準備好
Do you remember the galloping horse
記不記得外馬奔騰
Every county magistrate comes out and says it's ready
每一個縣長都出來說準備好了
Ready
準備好了
make a big impact
造成很大的影響
At that time, the DPP had a lot of corruption, what?
就他那個時候民進黨有很多腐敗的事情啊什麼
Ah Bian, the people below are going to gamble again.
阿扁啊下面的人又去賭啊
His wife is counting that again
他太太又在數那個
what is this receipt
這個收據還是什麼
therefore
因此
In order to revitalize Taiwan's economy, we must stop agreeing with the mobilization
與振興台灣經濟必須停止認同動員
Then
然後
Economic recovery and identity are upside down
經濟重振與認同是倒掛的
If you want to do a good job in the economy, you should stop doing that thing.
你要把經濟搞好呢你就不要再去搞那個東西
And in Taiwan at that time
而在當時的台灣
is audible
是聽得進去的
So the economic power of the electorate demands to be acquainted with the initiative for Taiwan's indigenous identity
所以選民的經濟力要求結識對於台灣本土認同的倡議
But let's not talk about this yet
但是先不要講這個吧
The economy is so bad right now
經濟現在情況已經這麼糟糕
that's better
這樣就更好吧
Such logic can gain the support of many voters
這樣的邏輯可以獲得很多選民的支持
Overall economic downturn
總體來講經濟的下滑
identification mobilization boredom
認同的動員的厭倦
The cross-strait relations I just talked about
跟我剛剛講的兩岸關係
The link between identity and economics
在認同跟經濟之間的連結
One is that we are worried when the economy goes down
一個是說經濟下去了我們擔心
One is that we can't stand the identification for too long
一個是說認同搞太久了我們受不了
One is that I want to boost the economy
一個是說我要把經濟拉起來
It is necessary to improve cross-strait relations
就必須要改善兩岸關係
improve cross-strait relations
改善兩岸關係
to accept a certain degree of one-China principle
要接受某一種程度的一中原則
To do so, one must accept the 1992 Consensus
要這樣做就必須接受九二共識
And you are going to talk about the 1992 Consensus
而你要去講九二共識
Of course you can't be high
你當然就不能夠去昂揚
your Taiwan independence identity
你的台獨的認同
so there is an instrumental link between the two
所以它兩個有一個工具性的連結
These three factors combined
這三個因素加在一起
You will find that the axis starts to shift
你會發現這個主軸開始轉變
First the KMT then the DPP
First the KMT then the DPP
from our point of view
是從我們看
When the KMT does this
國民黨這樣去做的時候
In fact, it has also gone through a process
其實它也經過了一個過程
In the mid-1990s the concept of China
在1990年中期了中國的概念
increasingly politicized
逐漸被政治化
And it became specific to mainland China
而且變成專指中國大陸
I used to grow up in our time
以前在我們那個年代長大了
it doesn't feel like that
不是這樣的感覺的
But it's getting more and more like this
可是它慢慢越來越這樣
So Chinese identity in Taiwan
所以在台灣的中國認同
gradually dissolve
就逐漸的消解
Chinese nationalism
而中華民族主義
it seems untenable
看起來好像難以為繼
The Democratic Progressive Party in this era of identity change
民進黨在這個認同轉變的時代中
Rise into great political gain
興起變成在政治上獲得極大的利益
But the KMT retreated all the way
但是國民黨一路後退
and it gradually takes a
並且它逐漸採取了一個
Vague and Fluid Position
模糊而又流動的立場
how does it say
它怎麼說呢
it first declares itself
它先是宣稱自己
Even if China is Taiwan
即使中國又是台灣
So come up with it and call it
所以搞出來又叫做
Republic of China in Taiwan
中華民國在台灣
both have
這兩個都有
And gradually increase the proportion of the second identity
而且逐漸增加第二個身份的比重
accent on the second scale
重音在第二音階
When the Kuomintang was in the presidential university in 2000
當2000年國民黨在總統大學中
After Lee Teng-hui was defeated and transferred to the green camp
敗選李登輝轉入綠色陣營以後
The traditional position of the Kuomintang
國民黨的傳統立場
Looks like there's no way to maintain
看起來好像沒有辦法維持
At least those in the KMT
至少國民黨裡合的人
think so
是這樣想的
So the KMT
所以國民黨
fall into opposition position
落入反對黨的地位
he lost the first time
他敗選了第一次
he is thinking
他在想
Of course less talk about recognition
當然少談認同
Now the government is the Democratic Progressive Party
現在執政部是民進黨
while the Democratic Progressive Party
而民進黨的時候
The economy has deteriorated
這個經濟有惡化的情況
Of course, they desperately attacked the Democratic Progressive Party.
當然就拚命攻擊民進黨
There is no way to properly handle Taiwan's economic crisis
沒有辦法好好地處理台灣的經濟危機
His transformation was natural
他的轉型是很自然的
The KMT began to enter by identifying with
國民黨開始進入由認同
transition to economy
向經濟的轉型
1990 2,000
1990年2,000年
In 2005, after entering and leaving the chairman of the Kuomintang party
2005年出入國民黨黨主席以後
He began to downplay the identity controversy
他開始淡化認同爭議
what did he say
他怎麼說呢
He said drug evasion was a legal option
他說逃毒是一個合法的選項
KMT on February 14, 2006
國民黨在2006年2月14號
published in the Liberty Times
在自由時報上刊登了一個
Advertising in the age of modernization
化時代的廣告
he said so
他這樣說
He keeps talking about political unity
他不斷談政局統一
I said Ah Bian scolded me to death, right?
我講阿扁罵死了對不對
next time
接下來以後
He never talked about it again
他就再也沒有談過這個東西了
Automatically unification
Automatically unification
so
所以
Made strategy ahead of presidential election
馬德策略在總統大選之前
take a step back
退後一步
Then act for the Democratic Progressive Party
然後動腳為民進黨
stop talking about this
不要再講這個東西
thank you all
謝謝大家
that's the ad
就是那個廣告
liberty times
自由時報
In February 2000, the interesting thing is that these Liberty Times lamps
2000年又年2月時後有趣的是這幾盞自由時報燈
how on earth is this written
這到底怎麼寫的呢
The Chinese Nationalist Party advocates competition in the spirit of democracy
中國國民黨競爭主張本於民主的精神
Taiwan has many possible options for the future
台灣未來有很多可能的選項
Whether it is the same independence or the maintenance of the status quo
不論是同一獨立或維持現狀
must be decided by the people
都必須由人民決定
The Kuomintang's claim
國民黨的主張
say you want to ask me
說你要問我呢
Although all three
雖然三種都可以
you ask me
你問我呢
Taiwan should maintain the status quo of the ROC
台灣應該維持中華民國的現狀
Circle it like this, right?
還這樣圈起來對不對
but one thing to note
可是要注意一件事
How about his whole discourse?
他整個論述的方法呢
to transform the Republic of China from a supreme constitutional and moral obligation
把中華民國從一個至高的憲法和道德的義務
This used to be in this part of the KMT
這個以前在國民黨的這一塊裡頭
there is no need to discuss
是沒得討論的
It has become a political proposition chosen by the public voters
變成了一個公選民抉擇的政治主張
it makes a big difference
這有很大的差別
It used to say you had to be loyal to the constitution
以前是說你要忠於憲法
than traditionally there is such a legitimacy
比傳統上就是有這樣一個合法性
With this tradition is the Republic of China
有這個傳統是中華民國
The founding father of the Republic of China cannot be relied on
中華民國國父什麼 依不過來
what are you talking about
這個是你什麼討論的
So call Han the Republic of China
所以叫漢為中華民國
What is Ma Britain's law now?
現在馬英國講法是什麼
Oh, you talk about independence
哎呀 你講獨立啦
Someone said unity
有人講統一啦
In fact, he didn't say that before, he didn't say that
其實他以前自己不說他這樣不講
Some people say that maintaining the status quo is me
有人講維持現狀就是我
Then he does a poll and finds that the status quo is the most
然後他做民意調查 發現維持現狀的人最多
That means I'm arguing for the status quo
就是說我是主張維持現狀
I don't object to you either. What about your method?
我也不反對你 你的方法呢
also has his reason
也有他的道理
It's okay if everyone likes him
如果大家喜歡他也未嘗不可
But mine is better
不過呢 我的更好
He turns himself into an option, a commodity in the middle of the political market
他把自己變成是政治市場中間的一個選項一個商品
Let everyone be free to decide
可以讓大家自由來決定
Rather than saying that under the norms of the law
而不是說在法律的規範底下
must
一定要的
The moral, obligatory, supreme thing
道德的 義務的 至高無上的這個東西
I used to look at it like this
以前是這樣看的
So in the process the horse has turned
所以在這個過程當中 馬已經轉了
Since 2006
2006年開始
KMT Freezes Identity Controversy
國民黨凍結認同爭議
emphasize
強調
economic importance
經濟的重要性
Then to ease cross-strait relations
然後要和緩兩岸關係
That's why Xiao Wanqiang's cross-strait common market emerged.
所以就出現了蕭萬強的兩岸共同市場
The 1992 Consensus with Su Qi became the main axis of the campaign
和蘇綺的九二共識成為競選主軸
Cross-strait relations are understood in terms of economic interests
兩岸關係上從經濟利益來理解
Utilize civil for economical transactions
利用民用對於經濟上的交易
Improve relations between the Kuomintang and the other side
為國民黨和對岸改善關係
provide a basis for public opinion
提供民意的基礎
In the KMT election campaign
在國民黨選戰策當中
economy is the main purpose
經濟是主要的目的
Cross-strait relations are tools for promotion
兩岸關係是促進制的工具
Freezing identity disputes is a necessary means to improve cross-strait relations
而凍結認同爭議是改善兩岸關係的必要手段
Such a logical layout
這樣子一個邏輯的這個鋪陳
It hasn't changed until today
一直到今天都沒有改變
so it's realistic
所以這是現實的
instrumental discourse
工具引性的論述
Quite different from the claims of instrumental ideology
跟工具意識形態的主張大不相同
The Democratic Party is totally different
國民黨已經整個不一樣了
KMT challenge Naro Narok refuses to give up at first
國民黨挑戰民意黨一開始拒絕放棄
Looks like a strong battlefield
看起來有力的戰場
Still put forward various proposals on the identity
依然在認同上提出各種倡議
I remember that time
我記得那個時候
Even the electricity bill supports IoT
連那個電費的上面都有支持物聯
put a lot of things on it
把很多東西上面
Roll the head into the face, the body is fresh, etc.
滾頭入臉 肌體新鮮等等
So you found a very interesting thing today
所以你今天發現一個很有趣的事情
What about blue and green? Blue fights blue, not green fights green.
藍跟綠呢 藍打藍不綠打綠的
The blue is not the green is talking about the classics
藍不綠在講 經經經經經經
Green always speaks, agrees, agrees, agrees
綠綠一直講 認同認同認同
So the competition between these two becomes
所以這兩個的競爭呢 就變得呢
It's not just a competition between blue and green
不只是藍跟綠的競爭
It's a competition between two different issues
而是兩種不同議題的競爭
In 2008, of course, there were various factors
在2008年 當然有各種因素了
but no matter
但無論如何
The two generations of Mingyue, the Congress and their classmates, will lose in both
明月兩代 國會跟同學中 雙中若敗
This number is very large compared with before
這個數字非常的大 跟以前比較起來
The numbers fifteen percent and seventeen percent
數字百分之十五跟百分之十七
Then tomorrow, the review will start.
然後明日呢 就開始檢討
Then in his mind, in fact, Tsai Ing-wen
然後在他的心目 其實蔡英文
Tsai Ing-wen is not the leader of any faction
蔡英文也不是任何派系的領袖
Tsai Ing-wen, our understanding is basically
蔡英文 我們的瞭解根本是
Lee Teng-hui suggested to Chen Shui-bian
這個李登輝建議給陳水扁的
And he just happens not to be from any faction
然後他剛好就不是任何派系的人
So he became the new chairman of the party
所以他變成了新的這個黨的主席
under his agency to begin the transformation
在他的代理下開始進行轉型
So the transformation of the Kuomintang and the transformation of the DPP
所以國民黨轉型 民進黨轉型
all because
都是因為
Because of electing the DPP after 2008
因為代選2008年以後的民進黨
Editorial Benefits of Any Same Momentum
任同動力的編輯效益
Doesn't it look tall?
看起來是不高嘛
That just so happens that he's in the opposition now.
那剛好他現在是反對黨
The KMT is the ruling party
而國民黨呢是執政黨
So the KMT's economic performance is very convenient
所以國民黨的經濟表現是很方便的
To evaluate the target, APPFIRE, house price,
去評目標、APPFIRE、房價、
The unemployed under this huge height
這個巨高之下的失業的
In fact, the government at the time of the 2012 case
其實2012 case那個時候的政府
I want to give this young man who has just come out of work
想要給這個剛剛出來就業的年輕人的
a concession
一個優惠措施耶
Pay attention to the lights
注意小燈吧
he gave him 2012
他給他2012
Because you probably didn't have a job at all.
因為你本來可能根本沒有工作啊
So the government pays some money
所以政府就付一些錢
Then these companies will use 22K
然後接下來這些企業就以22K這樣
Then look after this young man
然後來顧這個年輕人
As everyone knows, more companies are on the same page
殊不知更多企業就因此看齊
So your original 24K also jump to 22K
所以你本來24K的也跳到22K
so i complained so much
所以我就抱怨得很厲害
policies like this
像這類型的政策
Of course there are places to attack
當然有可以攻擊的地方
so in a sense
所以在某種意義來講
Tsai Ing-wen took the route of Ma Ying-jeou
蔡英文走上了馬英九的路線
how to say
怎麼說呢
In his mind, he leaned towards the middle
念頭上他往中間靠往
Let's think about Tsai Ing-wen
我們想一想蔡英文
We'll have a picture of him in our minds.
我們腦筋就會浮現一下他的樣子
his speech
他的講話
Then think about Chen Shui-bian
然後再想一下陳水扁
then he looks like
然後他的樣子
his speech
他的講話
can you feel it
你能覺得不覺得
The two of them seem to be from different planets
他們兩個像是從不同星球上來的人
very big difference
差別非常的大
he is alone
他一人在
year before running for president
競選總統的前一年
This sentence was spoken on the Double Tenth National Day in 2011
2011年的雙十國慶講的這句話
The Republic of China is Taiwan
中華民國就是台灣
But the meaning of this is actually what the Democratic Progressive Party has said
但這個意義其實本來民進黨也有講
But what he means by this is
但是他講這個意義就是說
you do not need to worry
你不用擔心
if i come up
我上來的話
I will not take away the four characters of the Republic of China
我並不會把中華民國的四個字拿掉
Many people for the Republic of China
很多人對於中華民國
is a note with a strong emotion
是有很強的感情的音符的
It means to go in the middle
這是往中間走的意思
realistic
現實的
His objection to APP
他對於APP的反對
A realistic economic standpoint
一個現實的經濟的立場
I remember that there are many advertisements of the Democratic Progressive Party
我記得好多民進黨廣告上面就有
like chamon et al
像查蒙等等
that is
就是說
If that EKFA comes
那個EKFA來的話
their livelihoods are affected
他們的生計就受到影響
he does not use ideological methods
他不是用意識形態的方法
come against him
來反對他
what he said was very realistic
他講的是很現實的
Tsai Ying-ming wants to organize Taiwan independence
蔡英明說要組張台灣獨立
Cai Yingming has a group Zhang Gong to join the alliance
蔡英明有組張公投入聯
Cai Yingming has a group certificate
蔡英明有組張證明
Tsai Ying-ming organized Zhang to make a constitution
蔡英明有組張制憲
These group sheets from the A-bian era
這些阿扁時代的組張
Cai does not speak at all
通通蔡都不講
Therefore, the Democratic Progressive Party has gradually shifted from political to economic
所以民進黨也逐漸從政筒轉向經濟
Also Freeze Policy
另外也凍結政策
Economy hangs over overall median voter appointments
經濟掛塞整體中間選民任命
but please when you go like this
但是請求你當你這樣走
when you walk like this
當你這樣走
What do you say about your life voters
你說你的生命選民怎麼辦
don't be afraid
一點都不要怕
He has no one but you to vote for
他除了你沒有別人可以投
Which one do you ask him to vote for?
你叫他投哪一九
In Namadang History Network, a Relying on People Versus Producing Voters
那馬當史網中一間靠民對生產選民
also the same
也是一樣
so
所以
This is the KMT's 2008 set of strategies
這是國民黨的2008的整套策異
Two middle walks happened
發生了兩中間走
result
結果
We have seen the DPP win for a decade
我們看到民進黨贏了一十年
A series of by-elections whose support is now picking up
系列的補選 它的支持度如今回升
In the 5th election in 2010, the total number of votes exceeded the KMT
2010年5度選舉當中的總得票數上超過國民黨
5% if you add up the county and city elections in the previous year
5% 如果你把前一年的那個縣市這個選舉加在一起的話
You will find that the DPP has more votes than the KMT
你會發現這個民進黨的總得票率是超過國民黨的
Although the DPP did not win back power in 2012
雖然2012年民進黨沒有贏回政權
But has significantly reduced the gap between the KMT
但是已經大幅減少了國民黨的差距
Congress is from 15 to 10 presidents, and from 17% to 6%
國會是從15到10總統 更是從17%到6%
i remember before that presidential election
我還記得在那個總統選舉之前
There are many predictions that Tsai Ing-wen may win
有好些預測的還認為蔡英文可能會贏
let you think about the situation at that time
讓你想想看那段時間的情形
Then she campaigned with her personal image, and her demands are far from the candidates of the Democratic Progressive Party in the past.
那她以個人形象競選 訴求跟往事的民進黨的候選有很大的差距
But some people like to hear it so much
可是有些人就這麼喜歡聽這樣講
But in fact she is quite similar to Ma Ying-jeou
但是其實她跟馬英九還蠻像的
isn't it
不是嗎
Received this education abroad
在國外受這個教育回白
She can't even speak Taiwanese correctly.
她的台語都講得不對
her english is very good
她英文非常的好
It's cold when she talks
她講話的時候比較冷
not easy to explain
不容易解惋
man ji ang this
人姬昂這個
that stirs up
那個鼓動情緒起來
I remember the night before the election
我記得常選前一天晚上
You go back and bless him
你都回去加持他
But when he's most emotional
但他情緒最姬昂的時候
It seems that you keep Taiwan's secrets
是好像你都把台灣的祕密
Give Tsai Ing-wen
抽脫給蔡英文
That person changed and said your action
那個人改動說你這個動作
not cai herself
不是蔡自己
Tsai Ing-wen is not that kind of horse
蔡英文馬都不是那種
Ji Ang's that can agitate
姬昂的那個可以鼓動
this
這個
just when you were there
剛你在那個地方
Hello everyone
大家好
call it this way
這樣叫一下
Then there are some gestures
然後還有一些手勢做起來
It feels like there is no way to be brought up by him.
感覺上就沒有辦法被他帶起來
These two are actually
這兩位其實都是
in the colder
處於比較冷的
such a presidential candidate
這樣的總統候選人
the leader
這個領袖
so interesting
所以很有意思
So we see that the KMT and the DPP
所以我們看到國民黨跟民進黨
learn from each other
相互學習啦
And learn from the lessons of defeat
並且從敗選的教訓中學習
KMT downplays his Chinese nationalism
國民黨淡化了他中華民族主義的色彩
adopt a hybrid identity
採取一種混合式的認同
then turn to economics
然後轉向經濟
Any mobilization and acceptance of economic
任何的動員並且接受經濟
as the main topic
作為最主要的議題
Both parties learn from defeat
兩黨都是從敗選中接受教訓
magan vegetables to a considerable extent
馬根菜相當程度上
converted their political parties
轉化了他們的政黨
However, we have to ask the transformation
然而我們要問這樣的轉變
Is it decisive
是不是具有決定性
And what might happen in the future
而將來可能會怎麼走
then continue to look down
那就繼續再往下看
there are three words
這有三個字眼
One is replacement
一個是 replacement
one is crisscrossing
一個是 crisscrossing
one is facade
一個是 facade
That replacement is to replace
那 replacement 就是取代
Is it possible for the economy to actually replace
有沒有可能經濟真的取代
Has identity become the main axis of political competition in Taiwan?
認同變成台灣政治競爭的主軸呢
if it is like this
如果是這樣的話
is to identify the relevant issues
就是認同相關的議題
no longer the main axis
不再是主軸
The economy becomes the core issue
經濟成為核心議題
Here I have three
這裡我留有三種
This shade of development
這個深淺不一的發展
One is the economic vote
一個是就是經濟投票
economic vote
就是經濟投票
Those who engage in economic voting are small
搞經濟投票的人都小的
There are some fine distinctions in it
裡面有一些那個很細的這個區分
Forward-looking is his retrospective is his society is his personal
前瞻是他回顧是他社會是他個人是
basically means
基本上就是說
Are you looking at the present or the future?
你是看現在呢還是看未來呢
Or you look at your pocket
或者說你是看自己的口袋
Or look at the whole society
還是看整個社會呢
Anyway, he just depends on the overall economic situation to decide.
反正他就是看整個經濟的狀況來決定
is it how to vote
是不是怎麼投票
completely determined by the economy
完全由經濟來決定
The second one I call distributive politics
第二個我把它稱作分配政治
That is to say, the two parties
就是說這兩個黨
It will combine with various interest groups
它會跟各個不同的利益團體結合
When you vote, it depends on which interest group you belong to
你投票的時候是由你是屬於哪個利益團體
Which party to vote for
因而由去投哪個黨
As is often the case in the United States,
像美國的情形常常會出現這樣的情況
In Europe it is often the case that
在歐洲的情形常常會出現
class vote
階級投票
Then I'd say I'm a Labor family
那我好比說我是一個Labor family
I have always been a laborer
我從來就是勞工
Then I have been a laborer for many generations
然後我這個多少代都是勞工
and then myself
然後我自己也是
So I'm full of this class history
所以我就充滿了是這種階級歷史
Then I will definitely work
那我一定就投工到
no problem anyway
反正沒有問題
no matter what
不管是哪一樣
It's all a form of substituting economics for identity
這都是一種以經濟取代認同的形式
We found that if we do
我們發現如果這樣做的話呢
then social divisions are unprecedented
那麼社會分歧就是有前無之下
turned the matter
將物質轉動了
KMT may transform into a center-right party
國民黨可能轉化成為一個中間偏右的政黨
The DPP may become a center-left party
民進黨可能會變成是一個中間偏左的政黨
if he doesn't
如果他不這樣做的話
may have to this class
可能有以這個階級
Left and right oriented parties will replace them
以左右為定位的政黨會取代他們
Normalization of Taiwan politics
台灣政治就正常化了Normalization
We take left and right as the main axis of competition
我們以左右為競爭的主軸
looks like western
看起來就很像西方
but of course
然而當然了
Of course, it is impossible to completely eliminate the love house that I agree with.
認同的情宿當然不可能完全消夾
It is difficult to hide the factors of mainland China
中國大陸的因素很難匿了
who knows what will happen to them
哪一個人曉得他們會怎麼樣呢
so of course we know
所以當然我們知道
This identity politics is likely to be faked again
這個認同政治很可能會再假播
Basically, as long as there is no that, it will slowly replace
基本上就是只要沒有那個就慢慢取代
this is the first possibility
這是第一個可能
The second possibility is that the appearance is a Façade
第二個可能是表象是一個Façade
What does that mean
什麼意思呢
The economy is just a mask for deep identities
經濟只是深層認同的面具
Economists on both sides of the strait supported by the Kuomintang and the Kuomintang
國民黨支持的兩岸經濟者和國民黨
Not because they want to revive Taiwan's economy
不是因為想要振興台灣經濟
But because it still has a unified love house inside
而是因為它內裡還是有統一的情宿
DPP opposes cross-strait economic integration
民進黨反對兩岸經濟整合
Not because of any economic and practical factors
也不是因為什麼經濟跟現實的因素
It is because its deep concept is to legalize Taiwan independence.
而是因為它的深層理念就是要法理台獨
So it is the enemy division for mainland China
所以它對於中國大陸就是敵師
The economic language and rational thinking used by both sides
雙方所使用的經濟語言跟理性思考
It's all fake appearances
都是虛偽的表面現象
truly influential
真正發揮影響力的
It is the deep recognition of the two parties and the two camps
是兩黨跟兩個陣營的深層認同
copy the language of the economy
抄著經濟的語言
identity
邁的是認同的實質
Sensibility actually surpasses rationality
感性其實超越理性啊
is that so
是這樣嗎
if legal
如果是法法的
not only political parties hypocrisy
不僅政黨虛偽
voters are hypocritical
選民也虛偽
Voters seem to accept rational economic discourse
選民看起來接受的是理性的經濟論述
In fact it accepts a bipartisan message
其實它接受是兩黨訊息中
emotion of identification
所蘊含的認同情緒
if it's not about you talking
如果重點不是你講說
How much
多少錢
How many percentage points does the unemployment rate increase?
失業率增加幾個百分點什麼
I hear what you think makes sense or doesn't make sense
我聽你覺得有道理或沒有道理
not by the soundness of your economic argument
不是由你的經濟論述的合理性
to decide
來決定的
but your statement
而是你那個論述
Identify with the one hidden deep within me
跟我自己內心深藏的那個認同
Can it be hooked together?
是不是能勾連在一起
If I think I can hook it up
如果我覺得可以勾連在一起
if i were blue i would say
如果我是藍的好必說
then i listen to you
那我聽你講說
The mainland has good development opportunities
大陸有很好的發展機會
why i go
為什麼我去
makes sense
有一點道理
If it's beneficial, I'll think of it
如果是利的我就想到
Oh no
糟糕了
Taiwan is doomed
台灣要完蛋了
The service industry is dying
服務業要完蛋了
All the electricity will go down like this
所有的電都要垮掉這樣子
In fact, it is your modification that is hooked up
其實被勾起來的是你的改性
Economic Issues Are Only Identity Issues
經濟議題只是認同問題的
derivation of issues
議題的衍生
It has no way of determining the voting behavior of voters by itself
它本身沒有辦法決定選民的投票行為
The main axis of Taiwan's politics is to identify with
台灣的政治主軸還是認同
The main social divide is still material
主要的社會分歧還是物質性的
inner identity
選民以他的內在認同
decide what party it is
決定這是什麼政黨
The economy is used to rationalize the given choices of the electorate
經濟是用來合理化選民的既定抉擇
This is the Façade
這是Façade
These three are named Chris Crossley Joe Chan
這三個叫Chris Crossley Joe Chan
Could the truth be between the facade
會不會真相是介於門面
It's between Fa Sa's and Replacement
就是Fa Sa的跟取代之間呢
Will it be economical and acceptable?
會不會經濟跟認同
They are the two axes of competition
他們是競爭的兩個軸線
And they also cross-penetrate
而且他們還會交互滲透呢
In terms of identity, let's say we talk about
認同方面 好比說我們講
Exclusive Taiwanese
有排他的台灣人
Exclusively Taiwan's trick
exclusively台灣的那一招
I am Taiwanese and nothing else
我就是台灣人 不是其他
Taiwanese are also Chinese
台灣人也是中國人
Now if we only talk about Chinese
現在如果只是講中國人
already reached the digits
已經到了各位數
Many with Chinese identity are in
有中國認同的很多都是在
Taiwanese and Chinese
又是台灣人 也是中國人
We call him Tc and the one before that is ET
我們叫他Tc前面一個叫ET
Then what about the economy
然後經濟方面呢
Left with redistribution and right with focus field
有重分配的左跟重視場的右
what am i talking about
我講的是什麼呢
That is, you can actually have these four combinations.
就是你其實可以有這四種組合啊
Then what
然後呢
Different regions, groups of people, one field
不同的地區 人群 一體領域
The relative salience of identity and economy
認同跟經濟的相對顯著性
It's Ratacus salient
它的Ratacus salient
and still different
而且還是不同的
this may be a comparison
這可能是一個比較
with a detailed view
跟細緻的看法
ok let's see now
好 我們現在就看
Echphal means
Echphal這個意思
assuming that economics is a more important consideration than identity
假設經濟是比認同為更重要的考慮的話
then let's see
那麼我們看看
If you identify yourself as Taiwanese
如果你是認同上覺得自己是台灣人
How much intimacy with the other side
就跟對岸有一個多少的親切感
Then your economic attitude is right
然後你的這個經濟上的態度是區右的
Do you feel more connected
你是覺得多一點聯繫
a little more contact
多一點的接觸
A little more is good for the overall economy
多一點的對整體的經濟是好的
if you have both
如果你是兩個都有的話
You are the pool of congenital
你就是先天之池
good
好
That
那
If we now assume that economic considerations outweigh recognition
如果我們現在假設經濟的考慮大於認同
So if you are in the lower right corner
那如果你是在右下角
The lower right corner means
右下角的意思是表示
you may or may not be
你可能是不一定都是這樣
Suppose there is such a person
假設有這樣子的人
For example, he is Japanese
比方說他是日本家
He opened a factory, or after the cross-strait communication
他開工廠的或者說兩岸的這個通了以後
it is beneficial to him
對他是有利益的
He's in shipping etc.
他是搞航運的等等
then he is on the right
那麼他是靠右
But his identification is very strong
可是呢他的認同很強
He is Taiwanese
他有就是台灣人
So the other side has a completely different democracy from mine
所以對岸跟我完全不一樣的民主
then you will get an attitude
那你是會取得一個態度
If you say that your economy is greater than your recognition
如果說你是經濟大於認同的話
these people will barely support
這些人會勉強不支持
Why
為什麼
Because the economy is more important
因為經濟更重要啊
good
好
if you are on the left
如果你是在左邊
Let's say you're the husband
就說比方說你是老公
you can't move
你沒有辦法移動的
It's not like money can go to the other side
不像錢可以到對岸去
Then you may be in a traditional industry
然後你可能是在傳統產業裡頭
You are afraid of competition from the other side
你很怕對岸的競爭
Then what if your identity is
然後呢如果說你的認同是
not Taiwanese
不就是台灣人
I don't accept what you said
我不接受你講那個什麼
We are all Chinese
我們都是中國人那一套
what not what to do is chinese
什麼沒有什麼做是中國人
Anyway, I heard the word Chinese
反正聽了中國兩個字
i can't accept it
我是不能接受的
what if that's the case
那如果是這樣的話呢
then you just
那你就
it's hardcore green
就是鐵桿的綠色的
you object
你就反對
Heaven is against this thing
先天上反對這個東西
But we feel more favorable
可是我們覺得更有利
because you are here
因為你是這裡的
If your golden status is on the left
如果你的金色地位是靠左
But any of you
可是你任何人上面
I feel that the other side is approachable
覺得對岸是可親近的
so what attitude do you take
那麼你會採取哪個態度
If we assume that economic ratios identify
如果我們假設經濟比認同
come more important words
來得更重要的話
then you will hesitate to object
那麼你會猶豫的反對
you still object
你還是反對
Why
為什麼
because you preoccupied the class position
因為你先佔階級立場
but you are hesitant to object
但是你是猶豫的反對
why
為什麼呢
Because the other side tells you
因為對岸跟你來講
still kind
還是比較親切的
So there is such a situation
所以就出現這樣的一個情形
ok let's go down
好 我們再往下
will make it clearer
會幹得更清楚一點
Well now it's time for the whole
好 現在已經到了整個的
This is the last paragraph
最後面這一段了
as if we were to see
就如果我們是看到
There may be an axis
目前可能有個軸線
If this turns
這個轉動的話
how do we do this research
我們如何來做這種研究
First
第一個
we should know
我們應該要知道
political party
政黨對於點販轉移的
What is perception and countermeasures
感知跟對策是什麼
picture
像
we just made this
我們剛剛做的這個
The other is to look at voters
另外一個是看選民
as far as voters are concerned
就對選民來講
identity and economy
認同跟經濟的
relative salience is what
相對顯著性就就是怎麼樣
Is it a replacement, a performance, or a crossover?
是取代 是表現還是交叉呢
if it is replaced
如果是取代
That is, if everyone thinks
就是說如果大家都認為
economics is more important
經濟比較更重要
Approval is not that important
認同沒那麼重要
Then I voted for this line
那我投票的這一條線
will emerge along this axis of the economy
會沿著經濟的這個軸出現
beyond identity
而跨越認同
That is to say, if I am left
就是說我如果是左的
i will vote
我就會投
Let us suppose
我們假設
That is to say, if the DPP moves to the left
就是說民進黨如果往左的方向
to develop words
來發展的話
I'll vote to the left
那我就投左的這一邊
If I am right
那我如果是右的
I vote on the right side
我就投右的這一邊
what is my own identity
那我自己的認同是什麼
this is not important
這個不重要
If it is appearance
如果是表象
that is to say it is fake
就是說這是假的
everyone basically knows
每一個人基本上知道
Vote with your own approval
自己的認同來投票
Then I voted this way
那我投票的這個方法
will emerge along the axis of that identity
會沿著那個認同的軸線出現
which length makes me feel
哪一個長讓我覺得
His identity is the same as mine
他的認同跟我一樣
I will vote for him
我就投他
Whether the party is left or right
不管這個黨是左還是右
what if it's a cross
如果是交叉呢
My voting line would be somewhere in between
我的投票界線會在前者兩者之間
i will become a slash
我會變成一條斜線
well what exactly
好 究竟是什麼
if we make it
我們如果做出來
as long as we vote all
就我們把所有投給
The vote of the Kuomintang
國民黨的這個票
put it in
都把它在
In this diagram of identity and economy
認同跟經濟的這個圖當中
mark it up
把它標誌上去
Then if we see the situation
然後如果我們看到的情形是
Those who voted for the Kuomintang and the blue
投國民黨跟藍色的票的
it's on the top piece
是在上面這一塊
who voted for the Democratic Progressive Party
而投民進黨的票的
it's in the block below
是在下面這一塊
we can find out
我們就可以發現
In fact voters
其實選民
The emphasis is on recognition
著重的還是認同
Why
為什麼
because it doesn't matter if you're left or right
因為不管你是左還是右
How do I know if you are left or right?
至於我怎麼知道你是左還是右呢
May ask by survey
可能靠 survey 問
Then wait and see how your left attitude is
然後等等看你左的態度如何
so i know if you're left or right
這樣我就知道你是左還是右
whether you are left or right
不管你是左還是右
As long as I consider myself Taiwanese
只要我認為自己是台灣人
I will vote green
我就會投綠的
As long as I feel that I am identifying with Taiwanese
只要我覺得自己在認同上面是台灣人
Chinese again
又是中國人
i will vote blue
我就會投藍的
Regardless of my own preference of being left versus right
不管我自己是在左跟右的偏好是什麼
that's my vote
我的投票就是這樣
But I mean another word
但是我是另外一句話就表示
like this key
像這個關鍵的
Still agree with this axis
還是認同了這條軸線
This axis divides the two kinds of people
這個軸線切分了這兩種人
This axis also splits two kinds of votes
這個軸線也切分了兩種票
You vote with your approval
你投票是跟你的認同去投的
So something like this
所以這樣的話
we're talking a lot of stuff now
我們現在講一大堆東西
In fact, Ai is all fake
其實阿艾都是假的
when i voted down
我投票投下去的時候
I am voting according to my sensibility
我是跟著自己的感性在投票
But if we make this picture and change it like this
可是如果說我們這個圖做出來變這樣
how is that
那是怎麼樣呢
That means I agree with people on the right
就是說我贊成右的人
Whether it's my golden status
不管是我的金色地位也好
Or my opinion of where the country is in this economy
或者說我對於國家在這個經濟中所處的
Policies, etc.
政策也好什麼等等
I am on the right
我是處於偏右的
I am right
我是偏右
then no matter
那麼不管
I said I am Taiwanese
我說我自己就是台灣人
Or I am both Taiwanese and Chinese
或者說我就是台灣人也是中國人
no matter what my identity is
不管我的認同是怎樣
i vote like this
我投票是一個樣子
then if i was left
那如果我是左
Just my golden one
就我金色的一位也好
Or I think the government should reduce the gap between rich and poor
或者說我覺得政府應該減少貧富差距
The government should increase welfare spending
政府應該增加福利支出
The government should tax some people more
政府應該多抽有些人一點稅
It's like I'm the one who thinks so
好比說我是這樣想的人
my kind of person
我這種人
It doesn't matter if I say I'm Taiwanese
不管我是講我是台灣人也好
Taiwanese or Chinese
台灣人還是中國人也好
No matter what my identity is
不管我的認同是怎麼樣呢
I always vote green and vote for the Democratic Progressive Party.
我通通是投綠的投民進黨這一邊
Then I found out the results of the poll
然後我發現投票的結果呢
This line is like this
這個線是這樣
This line just cuts between the left and right
這個線就剛好切在左右之間
Same as left and right cut
跟左右切的一樣
So when I voted
所以結果我投票的時候呢
regardless of my approval
不管我的認同了
I vote based on my financial interests
我投票是根據我的經濟利益來投票
This word is to replace
這個的話就是取代
But if what we get is this
但如果我們得到的是這個
i'm not messing with amoebas
我不是在搞阿米巴
Although they look a bit like
雖然他們看起來有點像
If we look at something like this
如果我們看的是這樣一個東西
that's a cross
那就是交叉了
what happens when you cross
交叉的話會出現什麼呢
let's watch this
我們看這個
who is this
這是什麼人
it's economic you're on the right
這是經濟上你是右的
ok
ok
Then you should vote blue
那你好像應該投藍
But what about agreeing?
可是呢認同上呢
you are guard taiwanese
你是警衛台灣人
But you still voted blue
但是你還是投了藍的
said for them
表示對於他們來說
economy over identity
經濟重於認同
so there will be
所以會出現
Such a piece of blue voter
這樣的一塊藍的投票的人
that's also in the lower right corner
那也是在右下角
also the same
也是一樣
These people should be economically right-wingers
這些人是經濟上應該是投右的
But in terms of identity, he is Taiwanese.
可是認同上呢他是台灣人
He voted green
結果他投了綠的
What about these people?
表示這些人呢
His reason is more important than
他的理性重於
He is more emotional than rational
他的感性重於理性
He is voting with approval
他是以認同在做投票
if we appear
如果我們出現這樣的話
Then these two pieces are explained like this
那麼這兩塊是這麼解釋
What about this piece?
那這一塊呢
it's just the opposite
這剛好相反了
he's in the upper left corner
他就在左上角
how do you say this
這是怎麼說呢
That is to say, economically, he is on the left
就是說經濟上他是左的
he should throw left
他應該投左
So he should vote green
所以他應該投綠的
but
但是呢
His identity is Chinese
他的認同呢是中國人
Also Taiwanese, he should have voted blue
也是台灣人 他應該投藍的
He should vote blue emotionally
他的感情上該投藍
His economy should be voted green
他的經濟上該投綠
if he casts blue
如果他投了藍
mean what
表示什麼
It means he is more emotional than you
表示他的感性超過你
If this piece appears
如果說出現這一塊
what is this piece
那這一塊是什麼
also the same
也是一樣
what is it
它是什麼
It is left on the golden position
它金色地位上是左的
OK
OK
but
但是呢
His identity above
他的這個認同上面的
Is the Chinese also this Taiwanese?
是不是中國人也是這個台灣人
He voted green
結果他投了綠的
what does that mean
那代表什麼
express his economic considerations
表示他的經濟上的考慮
beyond his approval of the above considerations
超過了他認同上面的考慮
Just if the two things are interpenetrating
就如果這兩種東西是互相滲透的話
Then the axis we see is not like this
那我們看到的軸線就不是這樣
if that is recognition
如果那樣的是認同
not so
也不是這樣
If so, it is economical but
如果那樣的話就是經濟而是
so
這樣
Such words mean
這樣的話的意思是表示
What about my lower right corner and upper left corner?
我的右下角跟左上角呢
How was it graded
怎麼樣被評分了
This means that identity and economy interpenetrate
這就表示認同跟經濟相互滲透
For some people, two identifications are more important
對有些人兩認同更重要
For some people the economy is more important
對有些人來講經濟更重要
bottom right and bottom left
右下角跟左下角
I can't look at the upper right corner and the lower left corner
我不會看右上角跟左下角
Because it's perfect blue and green
因為它是完美無缺的藍的跟綠的
I'll look at the bottom right and top left
我會看右下角跟左上角
They have interaction conflicts
它們有交互衝突
very anxious
很焦慮
my finances push me aside
我的經濟把我往一邊推
My finances push me the other way
我的經濟把我往另外一邊推
The result is split
結果分裂了
some people voted blue
一些人投了藍的
some people voted green
一些人投了綠的
This is to represent its two crosses
這樣就是代表它兩個交叉
interact with
跟交互作用
We can dampen the shock with something like this
我們可以用這樣的東西來加以減震
Of course now
當然現在的
For example, the one from TDS
比方說TDS的那個
I have read their latest survey
我有看他們最新的 survey了
There is a question about left and right
那裡頭要問到左右的那個題目
still bad question
還是問得不好
so there is no way to catch it clearly
所以沒有辦法很清楚的抓住它
But this piece of recognition
但是認同的這一塊
has developed a lot
已經發展了很多了
good
好
So for the main axis of political competition in Taiwan
所以對於台灣政治競爭的主軸
research on whether to transform
是否轉變的研究
I think it has great theoretical
我覺得具有重大的理論性
For Taiwan's political and
對於台灣政治跟
realistic
又有現實性
closely related to our actual politics
跟我們的實際政治密切相關
Taiwan's foreign relations
對於台灣的對外關係
Regardless of cross-strait relations
不管是兩岸關係
Or Taiwan-US relations have a major impact
或台美關係都有重大的影響
Therefore, it is a research worthy of high attention
所以是一個值得高度重視的研究
Dense
密成
Thanks
謝謝
Welcome to ask questions
歡迎各位提問
come please come
來 請來位
before asking the question
在還沒有問問題之前
I just listened to director Wu's speech, I believe
剛才聽吳所長的演講我相信
There is a passage inside Hamrabi's flower
哈姆拉比花的裡面有一段話說
Don't fight too long with female enemies
不要跟女的敵人打太久
become like him
變得跟他一樣
Especially when you mentioned Ma Yingjun's Tsai Ing-wen
尤其你講到馬英俊的蔡英文
more and more like
越來越像
do you believe this
是不是相信這段話
Don't fight your enemies for too long
不要跟你的敵人打太久
so as not to become more and more like him
免得跟他變得越來越像
come i want to ask
來 我要問
Thanks
謝謝
so to sum up
所以說總結
then i want to say many times
那我會想說很多次
You will also be normal to come to which one do you think
你也會是正常來到大家認為哪一種
will be guided very closely
就會被指導非常關係的
achievable
能夠實現的
So take care of what you need
所以說你自己需要的照顧一下
make the problem come back
讓問題要重來
under normal circumstances
在一般的事情之下
or Taiwanese society
或是台灣社會的
I think this seems to be more
這種我認為好像比較多上
is normal from to
就是正常來自到
The player's problem
這個選手的問題
So imagine in this direction
所以這個方向的想像
is it to be cared about
是不是要被關心
they'll pose like this
他們會擺出這樣
this question is very good
這個問題非常好
I agree with what you said
我同意你講的
That is to say, not everything can be seen as
就是說不能把一切都看成
society decides
是社會決定了
social determinism
社會決定論
I think there are two things to look at
我覺得可以有兩個東西來看
the first is
第一個就是
Of course, we can't see it as top-down
當然我們也不能夠看成是由上而下
In fact, every political party must
其實每一個政黨一定都會
Want to maintain the battlefield in your favor
想要維持對自己有利的戰場
So if I'm in a battlefield I can beat you up
所以我如果在有一個戰場裡頭我可以痛宰你
You said you don't want to play with me in this battlefield
你說你不要在這個戰場跟我玩
you're going to open another game
你要去開另外一個遊戲
Then of course I don't want to go there
那我當然不要過去
but the problem is
可是問題是
Recently my battlefield is real or your battlefield is real
最近我的戰場是真的戰場還是你的戰場是真的
we have to appeal to the voters
我們得要訴諸選民
right
對不對
Because I'm big on my field
因為我在我的戰場上大
Then I said I've been reading show
然後我說我一直讀秀
Then I realized that no one came to see my ring
然後發現根本沒有人來看我的擂台
He just went to see him so long
他就去看他那麼長
In the end, I just passed
結果我就只有過去了
So I think the manipulation from top to bottom
所以我覺得從上到下的操縱
has an inherent limitation
有一個先天的限制
This limitation is an effect on a larger environment
這個限制是對一個更大的環境所影響
what is the big environment
那個大的環境是什麼
In my whole analysis framework
在我的這整個分析框架裡頭
I think
我認為
Taiwan's economic development
台灣的經濟發展的情況
is a very important factor
是一個很重要的因素
And this factor makes voters think more and more about the economy
而這個因素使得選民對於經濟的考慮越來越重
But the Democratic Party does not mean
但是國民黨並不是說
Europe and the United States advocate the economy
歐美利主張經濟
So the DPP is attracted to this venue by me
所以民進黨都被我吸到這個場地
I went to the KMT basically to identify with that venue
我去了國民黨基本上是在認同那個場地裡頭
was beaten worse than Qing
被打得比清嚴重了
Then the proportion said
然後那位比例說
Okay, I won't come with you
好啦 就不跟你來了
I'm half throwing in the towel here
我在這裡就一半的認輸
Then let's play this now
然後我們現在來玩這個吧
it's not actually the action
它其實不是這個動作
if it doesn't do the first action
它如果不做第一個動作
The DPP can still pull it back
民進黨還是可以把它拉回去的
So I think
所以我覺得
The general environment prompts this axis to change
大的環境促使這個主軸有轉變
Of course the Kuomintang has some of its strategies
當然國民黨的那個它的一些策略
There is more to this shift
有更促使這個轉變
but you may ask a question
可是你可能會問一個問題
You said, let's look at Lebanon
你說那我們看黎巴嫩呢
Let's see Iraq
我們看伊拉克呢
We are optimistic about those Kuomintang
我們看好多那些國民黨
Relatives are finished
親戚可不已經完蛋了
These guys are still fighting, right?
這些人還在打 對吧
The rift where they fought each other
他們彼此互相相戰的那個切分裂痕
either else only read
都是要不然只讀取
otherwise only hit
要不然只中
The professional school hates the virtual school
職業派就恨虛擬派
Virtual faction hates that Kurd
虛擬派恨那個庫德人
and then make it like this
然後就搞成這樣
So I think another factor is
所以我覺得另外一個因素是
Identity Differences in Taiwan
台灣的認同差異
It's not that deep
其實沒有那麼深
it can be shifted to this side of the economy
它可以轉移到經濟的這邊來
When the environment will favor its transfer
當大環境會有利於它轉移
If its cut is very
如果說它的切是非常
I'm afraid there is no way
恐怕沒有辦法
let me give you an example
我舉個例子來講
We have good show scholars coming to Taiwan for a meeting
我們有好戲學者到台灣來開會
then we talk to him
然後我們跟他講
wow we're a blue and green opposite
哇 我們是一個藍綠對立的
Ours is badly weathered
我們的那個風化很嚴重
us people hate people
我們這批人恨一批人
then they told me
然後他們跟我講說
Really
真的嗎
He and I go outside to see if you are different
他我到外面看你們是不一樣啊
What am I talking about?
我說什麼話啊
we are just different
我們就是不一樣
I tell you
我跟你講
if you go to israel
如果到以色列那邊去的話
what is an israeli
什麼是以色列人
what is an arab
什麼是阿拉伯人
I can see clearly
我看得清清楚楚啊
they look different
他們長不一樣
speak differently
講不一樣的話
Doing different is living in a different place
做不一樣的是住不一樣的地方
what about you
你們呢
so just
所以就
we feel
我們自己覺得
The conflict is that Skeleton is here
衝突蠻就是那個Skeleton在這邊
In fact, relatively speaking, it is relatively mild
其實相對來講是比較緩和
because I feel
因為我覺得
On the one hand there is this
一方面有這個
On the other hand there is a big shock
另外一方面有一個大的驚氣的
causing Taiwan to swing between these two principal axes
使得台灣在這兩個主軸之間的擺動
is easier
是比較容易的
At least that's what I've seen so far
至少我目前看到的情況是這個樣子
so
這樣
But because of this time becomes
但是因為這個時候的變成
So it is a process of National Arts University
所以說是一個國藝大學的過程
But the Democratic Party
但是也就是國民黨
The KMT will not take gold for this
國民黨不會拿金色為這塊
Transfiguration University is because of the six
變形大學就是因為六人
But the KMT thing is a kind of
不過國民黨的東西是一種
won't become the whole combination
不會變成整個結合
The Democratic Party can't think so far
國民黨想不了那麼遠
Because when the DPP has reached the economic
因為當民進黨已經到了經濟
when this game comes
這個game裡頭來的時候
And when the KMT is the government
而國民黨又是政府的時候
It's just desperate to improve the economy
它只有拚了命來改善經濟
It must first maintain the situation
它先要把這個局給維持住
As for what you said, maybe in the long run
至於你講的說不定長遠來看
really become like that
真的變成那樣
it can't handle it
它管不了了
it's all about the next presidential election
它就接下來總統大選是它的一切
who else
還有哪一位呢
this one
這位呢
i'm curious that is to say
我很好奇就是說
Before we discuss these political rivalries in Taiwan
在我們討論這些台灣的政治競爭
compete with the economy
跟經濟競爭
When these active conversions
這些主動轉換的時候
External influence on Taiwan
外界的影響對台灣
Is it getting smaller
是不是變得越來越小
That is to say, Taiwan talks about many things behind closed doors.
就是也就是說台灣關起門來談很多的事情
Changes to the future under such development
在這樣的發展之下對未來的改變
Are we actually
我們是不是事實上
The more lack of a comparative force from the outside
越缺乏外面來的一個比較的力量
Because your two pancakes are so much better
因為你兩個小餅能夠比好到哪裡去
Then you lack a possibility to look outside
那你缺乏一個往外看的一個可能性
Just compare the direction of our media
就打比方向我們的媒體的
Some effects of receding in the middle
在中間退波除難的一些影響
Because I often feel like you turn off the TV
因為我常常覺得你把電視關起來
You think the world isn't so bad
你就覺得天底下沒有那麼糟糕
But when you turn on the TV
可是你把電視打開來的時候
In fact, many topics are not worth listening to.
其實很多的議題是不值得去聽
because there is little room for rational discourse
因為沒有什麼理性論述的空間
that negative impact
那這個負面的影響
Is it what you think it will be
是不是你覺得是會怎麼樣
drive change in our entire society
帶動我們整個社會的轉變
I think there are two parts to the story
我覺得話分兩頭來說
The first people in Taiwan are relatively lacking
第一個台灣的民眾比較缺乏
habit of looking outside
往外面看的習慣
Following the environment of the media has a lot to do with it
跟著媒體的環境是有很大的關係
this is a serious problem
這是個很嚴重的問題
For example, we don't really understand
比方說我們其實根本搞不清楚
Is our government doing well?
我們的政府做得好不好
What does that mean
什麼意思呢
Because I don't know what's going on in other countries
因為我並不知道其他國家情形怎麼樣
then let me give you an example
那我舉個例子來講
Like Merkel, he is a big camp
像梅克爾他算大營
recently in germany
最近在德國
The most important reason is that
那一個最重要的原因就是
Because Germans still look around
因為德國人還顧四周
It's even worse for France to step on Greece like this
法國這麼踩希臘更糟
Italy is outrageous
意大利不像話
Spain is doomed
西班牙要完蛋
All Europe is Germany
整個歐洲就是德國
very good
很好
So they think Merkel is amazing
所以他們覺得梅克爾很不得了
this is a comparison
這是個比較
Because Europeans are so close to each other
因為歐洲人彼此間是這麼接近
Do people in Taiwan have an overall international outlook?
台灣的民眾是不是有整個的國際觀
Then understand the environment we are in now
然後了解到我們現在所處的這個環境
and then judge our government by that
然後以此來評價我們的政府
I think we lack the ability to look outside
我覺得我們比較缺乏往外看的
for better or worse
不管是好壞了
Let's talk about this
這個再說
This is a
這是一個
Recently, a certain station is trying to pull our field of vision out
最近某台在試著要把我們的視野往外面拉
I wish him luck, but I really don't know how it will end up.
我祝他好運 但是我實在不知道最後結果會是什麼樣
In the past, there were quite a few programs that focused on international
以前有好些節目就是以國際的作為主要的
It didn't seem to go so well afterward.
後來好像都下場不是那麼好
OK but the other way around
OK 但是反過來講
On the other hand, is there any influence from outside?
另外一方面 外面是不是有影響到
that's the worst
這就是最糟糕的
The outside world greatly affects us
外面大大的影響到我們
But we don't know or we don't feel much
但是我們不知道 或者我們不去多感覺
External economic forces have trouble with Taiwan
外面的經濟力量對於台灣的風吹草動
We are so spiritually dependent on an outward looking economy
我們是這麼的靈靠外面的外向型的經濟
too much influence
影響太大了
There is a financial tsunami outside
外面來了一個金融海嘯
Isn't Taiwan the same as being blown up?
台灣不是一樣被吹得不得了嗎
Outside the economy, even the above things
外面的經濟上 甚至上面的事情
The situation on the other side
對岸的這些情形
The influence of the mainland on Taiwan is growing
這個大陸對於台灣的影響力越來越大
This itself is an objective fact
這個本身是個客觀的事實
But his rulers are in no rush
但他的執政者並沒有想要很急
fuck this thing
切的去操弄這個東西
so that its influence suffers
以至於它的影響力受到損失
I think it's smart to understand that
我覺得它很聰明的理解到這一點
But its influence is growing
但它的影響力是在增加當中
So let alone the United States
所以美國就更不用說了
and then a bunch of stuff
然後一大堆東西
Okay, so the outside world has a lot of influence on us.
好 所以外面對我們的影響力很大
But our understanding of the outside world is very small
可是我們對外界的理解是很小
I think it's the worst combination
我覺得是個最糟的組合
A better combination should be
比較好的組合應該是
The influence of the outside world on us is limited
外面對我們的影響力是有限
But I understand the outside world very well
可是我很理解外球的世界
Look how good it is, don't you?
你看這多好 不是嗎
Even I affect the outside
甚至我還影響外面
Then there is one more thing to say
那還有一個就是說
The field because we have a great influence
外業因為我們影響很大
But we also know the outside world well
可是我們也很了解外界
that's good too
這也好
If it weren't for the outside world's little influence on us
要不是外界對我們影響很小
we don't know the outside world
我們也不知道外面世界
Ah, you're old, at least count
啊你就故方至少算
We're messed up by outside influences, right?
我們是被外面影響一塌糊塗 對吧
how could we not
我們怎麼可能不是呢
But what we know about the outside world
可是我們對外界的了解
Actually less
其實是少的
Ah I
啊我
There must be many of you
我諸位當中一定有很多人
this is
這個就是
on our computer
我們電腦上面啊就是
Spend a lot of time blah blah blah blah blah
花很多時間啊什麼等等等等等等
i have a worry
我是有一個憂心的事情
as soon as i found out our tv
就我發現我們的電視
What is the news on the broadcast?
播報的新聞居然是什麼什麼什麼
let it truncate from internet speed
讓它從網速上截斷下來
Then you see this is exaggerated
然後就你看這個真誇張啊
it turns here
它居然在這裡轉彎
also met someone
還碰到一個人
You see, this knight just bounced off
你看這個騎士就彈飛出去的
Woooooo, auntie, play it ten times
嗚嗚嗚 阿姨你播個十次
And here's one of his most important news
然後這就是他一個最主要的新聞
something like this
像這種東西就
then what what
然後什麼什麼什麼
Then take a picture of that computer
然後就把那個電腦上照出來
What do netizens say
網友就說什麼
then what is the comment
然後評論是什麼
And he's not the only one
然後還不只有他這樣
This station does this
這個台這樣做
That station thinks that if I don't do this
那個台覺得我如果不這樣做
I seem to be behind
我好像還落伍
he did the same
他也這樣搞
I watch different channels
我看不同的台
He is still the same
他居然照是一樣的
the screen on the computer
那個電腦上面的畫面
This, this, if the medium of the Internet
這個這個如果網路的媒介
with traditional media
跟傳統的媒介
are highly concentrated in
通通都是高度集中於
to us
對我們
Everything related to daily life
一切日常相關
But it's all together
但是就是齊身的
this little piece
這一小塊東西
but didn't care
卻沒有去管
the big world outside
外面的大世界
Words that have had a huge impact on us
對我們巨大影響的話
then we are dangerous
那我們很危險
Because we are not very strong
因為我們力量也不很大
so i'm worried
所以我是擔心的
so i ask again
那所以我再問一下
So if it goes like this
所以如果照這樣講的話
Look at our media and the Internet
你看我們的那個媒體跟網路
Let's say they want to bomb an event
比如說他們要轟台一個事件
or an issue
或一個議題
Like the one a while ago
比如說前一陣子的那個
soldier that red
軍人那個紅
red mid autumn
紅仲秋
To Hong Zhongqiu's agenda
對 紅仲秋的他的議題
that is
就是說
many people would think that
很多人會認為說
he is a civic movement
他是一個公民自發運動
is a movement of civil disobedience
是一個公民不服從的運動
then on top of the blue and green parties
然後是在藍綠政黨之上
spontaneous
自發性的
Spontaneous demands of the common people
老百姓自發性的要求
government reform
政府改革
But from a certain point of view
可是從某種角度來講的話
because every day the media
因為天天都被媒體
play like this
這樣子的播放
That's how much of it is the spontaneous thinking of real citizens
那是中間有多少是真正公民自發的思考
That, or how do we break through this situation?
那或者是說我們怎麼去突破這樣子
Such a dangerous situation in Taiwan
台灣這樣一個很危險的狀況
That is to say, we are actually a very fragile economy
就是說其實我們是非常脆弱的一個經濟體
But we don't care about the changes we find around us
可是我們去對四周發現的轉變毫不關心
I think it's like Hong Zhongqiu.
我覺得像洪中秋這個事情
Did you say there was manipulation?
你說有沒有操縱 有
Did you say there is media amplification?
你說有沒有媒體放大 有
But you said he has touched a lot of people?
可是你說他有沒有打動很多人
It will come out automatically, too.
很自動的要出來 也有
I know there are a lot of them, it's just like the civil world
我知道有很多 那根本就跟公民世界
What faces too much correlation
什麼面臨太大關聯的
Which means he wasn't very involved at all.
就是說他根本也不大參與
For example, Mommy is at home
比方說媽媽他在家裡頭
After he saw this, he hated the sky
他看到這個事情以後他很意憎天
Because why does he think he is a child
因為什麼他覺得他小孩
Looks like his kid is hurting too
好像他的小孩也在受傷
So you said that the speculation on the Internet is so fierce
所以那你說這個網路上炒得這麼兇
And it seems like there's nothing fair about it
又好像沒有什麼公正的東西
not bad at all
一點都不錯
I think we lack a common ideal
我覺得我們缺乏一個公共的理想
room for debate
的辯論空間
we lack such a thing
我們缺乏這樣一個東西
one that lets in different voices
一個讓不同的聲音進來
And as long as you come in
而且只要進來了以後
let's just say you're in the middle of this
我們就說你在這個中間
no passion
不可以搞激情
but speak well
但是好好講話
Then many people would like to see
然後有不少人願意看
such a thing
這樣一個東西
We lack that public forum
我們缺乏那個公共論壇
we all have a stand
我們都有個立場的
If you say to watch this station
如果你說去看這個台
then his talk show
然後他的談話性節目
He will also find a partner
他也會找一個對方
The people who are in the camp are coming
正營的人來
but then attack him
但接下來就攻擊他
beat him up
把他打爛
Then see him speechless
然後看他講不出話來
Right
對吧
there too
那邊也是有
but this is not
但這個就不是
Then the whole discourse
然後整個的論述
have that one-sided nature
都有那種一面倒的性質
but there is no place
但也沒有一個地方
be able to say no matter what you look like
能夠說不管你看起來
emotionally not
情感上不是
how unacceptable
多麼的不是那麼能夠接受
But you let him finish talking properly
可是你讓他好好的講完
then listen to
然後聽聽看
I have my own reasons
自己也有他的道理
this public domain
這個公共的領域
I think in this field
我覺得在這一塊領域
if bigger
如果越大的話
our whole society will be different
我們這整個社會會不一樣
But we are relatively lacking in this area now
但是我們現在比較缺乏這個領域
We've done a great job of pasting tickets.
我們貼票簽貼得太厲害了
So you're saying we don't have a free press?
所以你說我們是不是有新聞自由
Oh, why not?
哎呦啊怎麼沒有啊
but we
可是我們
In a few examples
在幾個例子來講
If we talk about politics, this goes to one side
如果說政治這卻往一邊走
Because your press is actually a
因為你新聞界其實也是一個
to fight for the market, right?
爭取市場的嘛對不對
So can you do politically incorrect reporting?
那你能夠做政治不正確的報導嗎
It's actually stressful
它其實有壓力啊
So I think there's a civic culture
所以我覺得有一個公民文化
A culture that allows us to address these issues
這個文化能夠讓我們對於這些議題
able to make a rational argument
能夠做一種理性辯論
we have seen this kind of thing
這種東西我們有看到
it's a pity
覺得蠻可惜的
I think we should find a way to make something like this come out
我覺得應該想辦法讓這樣一個東西出來
I don't care about individual issues now
我現在不管個別的議題了
I mean anything on this topic
我是講說任何這個議題上
There should be something like this
應該有這樣一個東西
Teacher, I want to go back to some of the arguments mentioned in your speech just now
老師我想回到你剛才的那個演講裡面所提到的一些論點
and then do some clarification
然後做一些釐清
That’s what the teacher just mentioned about identity and economics.
就是老師剛才有提到說那個認同跟經濟這些
At a time of shift as the axis of political competition could be his electoral defeat
在作為政治競爭軸線的轉換的時候可能是他選舉失敗的時候
So his party started to have some shifts
所以他的政黨開始有一些轉變
Then I remember when Chen Shui-bian came to power in 2000
那我記得2000年陳水扁上台的時候
He mentions four emails
他提四部Email
Then
然後
Shouting slogans to fight the economy
喊口號拼經濟
Then have a development meeting
然後開進發會
At that time, it felt like he was freezing his identity too.
那時候感覺他也是在凍結認同
Instead, the axis of competition should be developed towards the economic aspect.
而是要把那個競爭的軸線往經濟的那個面向去發展
until that said
那直到說
When Dianjia was avoiding the dark, he began to go to extremes
典家發生避暗的時候他開始走極端
So I started to bring up the issue of recognition again.
所以開始把認同這個議題又重新拿出來操作
That
那
My first question is whether there is any way to answer the teacher's speech today
我的第一個問題是說在老師今天的演講的架構裡面有沒有辦法來回答
For example, in political operations like this, they are
比如說像這樣子的政治經營他們在
When the axis of my political competition shifts
我這個政治競爭這個軸線轉換的時候
like Chen Shuibian
像比如說陳水扁
His selection strategy at that time
他那時候的選擇策略
Why didn't I continue to expand the development of the economic axis
為什麼不是我持續擴大經濟軸線的發展
Instead I turned to the competition to identify with this
而是我轉向了認同這個的競爭
The second question is
那第二個問題是說
The teacher is in the conclusion part
老師在conclusion這個部分
Just mentioned three possibilities
就是提到了三種可能性
what i want to know is
那我想要了解是說
It's the teacher, if you yourself
就是老師您自己假若
You must now represent Taiwan's future politics
你現在要必須替台灣將來的政治的
development or society as a whole
就是整個發展或是社會的
Whole development of images to make a whole paragraph or assertion of words
整體發展的圖像做一個整段或論斷的話
Do you think Taiwan is moving towards this replacement performance or crossover
你覺得台灣是走向這取代表現或交叉
It’s the teacher, which direction do you think it is more?
是老師你會覺得是比較是走向哪一種的方向
Thank you for these two questions
這兩個問題謝謝
about the first question
關於第一個問題
In fact, this is a big framework
其實這是一個大的這個 framework
It is unlikely that it can account for every individual
它不大能夠解釋每一個個別的
How about you Bian
你阿扁的情形
I think it's Taiwan's identity energy
我覺得其實是台灣的認同能量
not fully mobilized
並沒有被動員充分
so when he tapped him again
所以當他再去tap他的時候
he actually got a nice reaction
他其實得到一個不錯的反應
only if he keeps going
只有當他不斷地去
to practice this energy
去施修這個能量
At last he found that he had
最後他發現他已經
when approaching the gas mother
接近告氣母的時候
at this time will be forced to transfer
這個時候會被迫要轉移
so everyone is trial and error
所以大家都在嘗試錯誤
when the leaders of these parties
當這些政黨的領袖們
When deciding which strategy to adopt
再決定要採取哪個策略的時候
He can't do that
他做得不見得就是
true to his best
真實對他最好的
he's trying to do it
他是試著這樣去做
Ah Bian's strategy at that time
阿扁當時所走的策略
In fact, it's not just about staying out of the dark.
其實並不是只說避暗出來
It should be said that in 2003
應該說在2003年
even earlier
甚至於更早一點
2001 2002
2001年2002年
One country actually came out when Nauru established diplomatic relations
一邊一國其實在諾魯建交的時候就出來
Then in 2003
然後到了2003年的時候
There is a SARS on it
上面有一個SARS
then next
那接下來就
connected to
連接的就到
Because Sha Zukang from the mainland is not there
因為大陸的沙祖康不是在那裡
Tell me who cares about you or what
講說誰理你們還是什麼
At that time, Taiwan felt
那個時候台灣就覺得
wow we look like this
哇 我們這樣子
We have no way to be received in the world
我們還沒有辦法在世界上面受到
You still feel sorry for us
你還這樣子悲隔我們
He also said that if you want to talk to the World Health Organization
還說好像如果要跟世界衛生組織
as if there is any connection through it
有任何聯繫要透過它似的
This thing suddenly becomes a
這個東西一下子就變成一個
Strong, intensified, this thing
很強的這個激化的這個東西
Then in 2003
然後到了03年
When the Democratic Progressive Party celebrates
這個民進黨黨慶的時候
Did he mention three tasks?
他提三大任務嘛
At this time, it has already been highly tuned out.
這個時候就已經很高的調出來了
Then there was the matter of the referendum
然後就有講那個公投的事情
So I think the operation of its election issue is
所以我覺得它的選舉議題的操作是
You said there was nothing wrong with the economy in the beginning
你說一開始經濟沒有錯
But the economy at that time
但是經濟在那個時候
just a very unfavorable situation
剛好是一個很不利的情況
Since 2000 began to decline
因為2000年開始往下跌
2001 Didn't you say rich
2001年 你不是說富的嗎
Never had
從來沒有過
Of course 2002 was only slightly better
當然2002年只是稍微好一點
So in 2003
所以2003年的時候
you are unlikely to be a ruling party
你不大可能作為一個執政黨
just mentioned
剛剛講到
According to this good economic performance
按照這個好的經濟成績
you have to vote for me
你們要投我的票
Actually for him
其實對他來講
shift to the positive side of identification
轉移到認同的正面去
There is also his motherhood quotes exist
也有他的母性引測存在
Of course there are risky leads
當然也有冒險的引測存在
Bian is a person willing to take risks
阿扁是願意冒險的人
And he risked it
而他簡冒下去
There is this energy that is really mobilized by him
有這個能量確實被他動員起來
I will actually have an impact on SARS in 2003
我其實會對2003的SARS產生的影響
I think we kinda understudied him
我覺得我們有點understudied他
Because of this thing in that paragraph
因為那一段的這個東西
The emotional impact on everyone is too great
對大家的那個影響感情打擊太大了
is very very
是非常非常的
Because it's a matter of life for everyone
因為這對每一個人就是生命攸關的事情
So if this thing
所以如果說這個東西
able to talk about serious issues
能夠跟一些正經議題
link together
link在一起的話
He has a lot of mobilizing energy
他有個很大的動員的能量
Anyway, that's what I meant to say
anyway 反正我的意思就是這樣說
Why did Ah Bian take this
阿扁為什麼採取這個
Because he wants to be under the situation that the economy is not easy to mobilize
因為他想要在經濟不好動員的情況底下
to try to mobilize another piece
去試著動員另外一塊
And after mobilizing this piece
而這一塊動員了以後
In fact, it has the effect of his weakness
其實產生他的這個弱感的效果
The person who Virus has risk taking is related again
Virus has risk taking的人又有關係
But my big structure
但是我的那個大架構
Although there is no way to explain
雖然沒有辦法能解釋
individual behavior
它貶的個別行為
can explain
卻能夠解釋說
If you mobilize mobilize mobilize mobilize to find
如果你動員動員動員動員發現
When the energy cannot be mobilized
動員不出能量的時候
you will be forced to change
你會被迫的要改
So it has that big predictability
所以它有那個大的預測性
But some small ones don't know
但個別小的這個就不知道
its all trial and error
它大家都在嘗試錯誤
Then the second one you just mentioned
那你剛剛講的第二個
I think
我認為
Which direction do I go?
我哪一個方向走呢
i think chris crossing
我覺得Chris crossing
yes there is a certain possibility of it
是有它一定的可能性
but like i said
但是就像我剛剛說的
Its external environment is the economy
它外在環境是那個經濟
so that thing
所以那個東西
if under its shadow
如果在它的籠罩底下的話
will indeed have its influence
確實會有它的影響力
But there is one more thing to note
可是還有一點要請注意
when i talk about axis shift
當我講說軸線轉變的時候
There are economic factors
有經濟因素
factors that identify with mobilization
有認同動員的因素
There is also the factor of cross-strait relations in the middle
也有兩岸關係的那個因素在中間
But this discourse in the middle
但這中間這個論述
In fact, it is very instrumental
其實它是很工具性的
it means to say
它的意思是說
economy is important
經濟很重要
not so much recognition
認同沒那麼多
For the good of the economy
為了經濟好
We must improve cross-strait relations
我們要把兩岸關係弄好
so don't make too much recognition
所以就不要多搞認同
If cross-strait relations are on schedule
如果兩岸關係如交如期
Our economy is still in shambles
我們的經濟情況卻仍然一絕不振呢
that middle tool twist strap
那個中間的工具扭帶
easily torn
就容易被撕裂了
once it's ripped
一旦它撕開了以後
you don't have to say
大家就不必為了說
to do a good job in the economy
要來把經濟搞好
So we have to follow the other side
所以我們就必須要跟著對岸
Let's talk about the 1992 Consensus or what?
一起去講九二共識還是什麼
not at all
根本沒有嘛
If this becomes a common thought of many people
如果這個變成一個很多人的共同想
That also refers to the axis rotation we just talked about
那也講到我們剛剛講的軸線轉動
so
所以
hello teacher two
二老師好
I just want to ask a question
就是我想問一個問題是說
Then we talked so much about the transformation of the axis of political competition in Taiwan
那我們前面講了那麼多關於台灣的政治競爭的軸線的轉變
So if Beijing as a foreigner
那麼就是如果北京作為一個外國人
he came to talk
他來看說
So Taiwan is now undergoing a transition from political competition to economic recognition
那台灣現在出現從政治的這種競爭往經濟的這種認同的方向的轉變
Then he personally said that he wanted to see this kind of criminal transfer
那他個人是說是希望看見這種犯事的轉移
I still hope that it will be more beneficial to face him on the ideological battlefield of the original two-party competition
還是希望在原來的兩黨競爭的意識形態的戰場上面對他比較有利
Because in fact, Beijing, on the one hand, for example, we have him and ACFA
因為其實北京他一方面譬如說我們有他有ACFA
He has Fumao to infiltrate Taiwan's economy
他有福貿來滲透台灣的經濟
He came to reinforce what the teacher said you brought
他來強化老師說講的你有帶的東西
But recently there was an article in Beijing that said
但是最近前一段時間北京的有一篇文章是說
He thinks that the KMT has sunk me down
他認為國民黨已經我向下沉淪
He thinks he said that the Kuomintang has begun to withdraw from the field of ideology
他覺得他說國民黨已經開始從意識形態的領域退出
Don't talk about the unification of China or the unification of the two sides of the Taiwan Strait
不去講統一中國或者是講兩岸統一的那個東西
So he actually has a little anxiety in his heart
所以他其實內心中間有一點焦慮
So the teacher's point of view is that
所以那老師的觀點是覺得說
In the end, this kind of typical profession is for Beijing
到底這種典範專業對北京來講
What would he prefer to see
他更希望看到的是什麼樣子
Thanks
謝謝
I think what Beijing wants to see is
我覺得北京希望看到的是
Everyone knows that Taiwan's economy
台灣的經濟大家都認識到
Mainland China's goodwill towards Taiwan can boost Taiwan's economy
中國大陸對台灣的善意能夠讓台灣的經濟起來的情況下起來
The focus is not on Taiwan's economic growth
重點不是台灣的經濟起來
Everyone can feel that cross-strait relations have a great impact on Taiwan's economy.
大家可以感覺得到兩岸關係對於台灣的經濟
is so important
是這麼重要
In this way, the people of Taiwan will
這樣台灣的民眾會為了現實的利益
while maintaining the existing framework
而維持住既有的框架
Even going one step further with mainland China
甚至於跟中國大陸更進一步
I think the police should think like this
我覺得在警察應該會這樣想
But he must have thought it wasn't enough
但是他一定覺得這是不夠的
He must be thinking about consciousness
他一定會想在意識上面
can have further links
能有更進一步的連結
I think the decision makers in Beijing
我覺得北京的決策者
I talked to many scholars in the mainland
我跟大陸的很多學者
they also talked
他們也都有談過
They feel as though economically
他們很感覺到好像在經濟上
Let the mainland's point of view
讓大陸的觀點
seems to be economically
好像在經濟上面
Also good for Taiwan
也台灣好處
Useless
沒有用
give him a lot of benefits
給他很多好處
unnamed example
不有名的例子
The swabfish from Xuejia
學甲的那個拭目魚
As a result, has there been any change in the voting orientation of Xuejia?
結果學甲有沒有投票取向改變
no it's still green
沒 它還是綠的
So vote your money for the DPP
所以按你的錢投給民進黨
is this
這是不是
so he was thinking
所以他在想
Is there something deeper that matters more
是不是一個更深層的東西更重要
he will feel
他就會覺得
culture matters
文化很重要
So he will want to evoke in Taiwan
所以他會想要喚起在台灣
The kind in the earlier period
比較早的那個時期裡頭的那種
The one about Chinese culture
對於中國中華文化的那個
the sense of belonging, the sense of nostalgia
歸屬感 那個眷戀感
And he often bullies
而且他就常常大欺負
I already feel that we used to engage in the Cultural Revolution
已經覺得我們以前搞文化大革命
you say we're doing it wrong
你們說我們做得不對
now our sister
現在我們妹妹
The same college makes it all over the place
同學院到處弄起來
we didn't get it right
我們沒對這一套
seems less interested
好像不那麼感興趣了
Actually, I think his voice
其實我覺得他講出來的聲音
I mean we're a lot like you
是說我們跟你們很像
like the recent one
像最近的那個
The mainland wants the basic textbook of Chinese culture
大陸要把那個中華文化基本教材
In fact, I want to refer to some of Taiwan's
其實我要參考部分台灣的
This also became their student
也變成他們學生的這個
his feeling is
他的感覺就是
Ah, this is Chinese
啊 這是中國人嘛
Is this what you're thinking of?
想的是這樣的事情嘛
why divide
幹嘛去分啊
but what
可是什麼什麼
something like this
這類的東西
so he will feel
所以他會覺得
It is also important culturally
在文化上這個也很重要
He for the KMT
他對於國民黨的那個
that quit that battlefield
那個退出那個戰場
feel very disapproving
覺得非常不以為然
There used to be a famous
大陸曾經有過一個很有名的
The head of the think tank is Zheng Bijian
那個智庫的大佬叫鄭碧堅
He once led the mainland
他曾經率領大陸
A group of scholars went to Taiwan to talk with these scholars in Taiwan
一群學者跑到台灣來跟台灣的這些學者對談
Many of these scholars are blue
那這些學者裡頭很多是藍的
Then these scholars also arranged to find one
那這些學者他們也安排了找了一位
Everyone knows our good friend Chen Yindong
大家都知道我們的好朋友陳寅東
He is from Lu, right?
他是陸的嘛對不對
Then served in this MAC
然後在這個陸委會服務過
Then he got up and read a passage
然後他就起來念了一段
Then say hello, my opinion is actually different from yours
然後講說嗨我的看法其實跟你們不一樣
it doesn't matter
那這個沒有關係
Anyway, I expected this sound to be there
反正料到這個聲音一定會有
What he can't understand the most is Ma Ying-jeou
他最不能理解的是馬英九
Why are there such a group of people around?
周圍怎麼有這麼的一群人
Talk like the Democrats
講話跟民進黨一樣
this is what he thinks
他的想法是這樣
So he thinks it is possible to strengthen the culture
所以他覺得在文化上面能不能夠再加強一點
And then very worried about Taiwan's change of use
然後非常擔心台灣的用途轉變
And then on the other hand
然後另外一方面呢
before that happened
在那個還沒有發生的時候
Economically, we should try our best to keep Taiwan in check.
在經濟上盡量能夠拉住台灣這樣
That's not Beijing's grand strategy, is it?
那不是北京的大戰略吧
Excuse me
請問一下
left and right Kuomintang and Democratic Progressive Party
左右國民黨跟民進黨
future words may be said
未來的話有可能是說
left and right
左派跟右派
Each party has its own ideas
同個黨都有各自的想法
not that i'm specifically left or right
不是說我專門左派或右派
or
或者是說
Like the KMT, their logic concept is derived from
像國民黨他們的邏輯觀念是從
The economy is not good because the cross-strait relations are not good
經濟不好是因為兩岸關係不好
If cross-strait relations are not good
兩岸關係不好的話
I want to promote it, that is to move closer to China
我要推動起來那就是跟中國靠攏
So he keeps saying that economy and identity are correlated
所以說他一直說經濟跟認同是互相關
So it is the emergence of the 1992 Consensus
所以說還要就是九二共識的出現
That's like saying vitamins have ABC's
那樣的話就像是維他命說有ABC
But you say A is a vitamin and nothing else
但你就說A是維他命其他都不是這樣
in that case would you feel this
那樣的話會不會覺得這個
This logical concept is a bit strange
這個邏輯觀念有點奇怪
Then there is the 1992 Consensus
然後還有九二共識
That is, China and Taiwan are singing separately
就是中國跟台灣各自唱歌
In fact there is an international
事實上還有一個國際
Then do you think it's just a kid arguing over there?
那你會不會覺得就是個小朋友在那邊吵
just feel
就覺得
very unreasonable
很沒有道理
Then there was the KMT who suppressed trade unions before
然後就是國民黨他們之前壓制工會
But they don't raise money, do they?
但是他們並不籌錢吧
Because they can get those properties from the moment they come
因為他們從一來的時候就可以得到那些財產
Then he doesn't need any union support.
那的話他就不需要什麼工會的支持
that's it
就是這樣子
Yes, the KMT does not need the support of the trade unions
對啊 國民黨不需要工會的支持
So he is not a leftist party
所以他不是左人正黨
then you just said
然後你剛剛講
Is this an international look at these two kids fighting?
這是不是國際上看這兩個小孩子吵架
You can also say yes
也可以說是啊
Not as if we see the Scots he wants independence from England
不是好像我們看到蘇格蘭人他要從英國獨立
we probably don't feel anything
我們可能也沒什麼感覺
ok the scots have a lot of feeling
好的 蘇格蘭人很有感覺
Because the Scots have a lot of feeling
因為蘇格蘭人很有感覺
how we look
我們看起來是怎麼樣子
But if you watch some movies, you might feel something
但如果看一些電影可能會有一些感覺
good
好
But don't fight about matters of international concern
但是國際上在意的事你們不要打起來
I remember I used to go to Singapore to take a taxi
我記得我曾經到新加坡去坐計程車
that time happened to be
那個時候剛好是
At that time, it was not the era of Chen Shuipi, it was the era of Lee Teng-hui
那個時候還不是陳水平的時代是李登輝的時代
He immediately rebuked
他就急人逆斥了
Because of you, what are the Taiwanese doing?
因為你怎麼台灣人在搞什麼
why is he so nervous
為什麼他就那麼緊張
I also want to be so fierce.
我也想那麼兇幹什麼
He said that we are going to give the stock a big drop today
他就說我們今天要給股票大跌
it means you get nervous
就是說你弄得緊張
war may follow
接下來可能有戰爭
Because of the war, the economy of the entire region will be affected
因為有戰爭說整個區域的經濟就會受影響
will suffer this loss
會受這個損
So what everyone thinks is you don't fight
所以大家想的是你不要打起來
So the international thinking is actually like this
所以國際上的想法其實是這個樣子
But there is also constant international hope
但國際上也不斷的希望
Taiwan and China are getting closer
台灣跟中國大陸走得很近
Because they are afraid of China's rise
因為他們對於中國崛起是害怕的
Then you think that if Taiwan and China are combined together
然後你覺得如果台灣跟中國整個合在一起的話
They are big wars
他們是大戰加大
then i recognized them
那我就認過他們
I say yes
我說好
you don't want us together
你不希望我們在一起
put them on
就把他們對
But he's right
不過他不是就對啦
just say you're right
就說你對
just get too close and i'm in danger
就太近我是危險的
real
真的
What do you say
那你說
What are you willing to give to Taiwan?
那你願意給台灣什麼
Let Taiwan not be so demanding of mainland China
讓台灣不至於這麼有求於中國大陸
Then you have to sell five thousand Taiwan
那你要賣五千個台灣
would you like
你願意
Are you scolding Beijing for being unhappy with promoting relations with Taiwan?
你罵著北京的不高興跟台灣提升關係嗎?
He said he wanted to maintain a good relationship with such a big
他就說他要跟這麼大的維持好的關係
For this he sacrificed Taiwan
為了這個他犧牲台灣
And when Taiwan I want to develop some relations with the mainland
而當台灣我想跟大陸發展一些關係的時候
He has started to blame Taiwan
他有開始指責台灣
But he can't give Taiwan any benefit
但是他就不能給台灣任何的好處
so that
所以那個
Internationally, it is actually very realistic.
就國際上其實是很現實的啦
don't fight
你不要打起來
then you stop
然後你就站住
your current situation
你現在這個情況
Then
然後
don't get too close to him
你也不要跟他太近
Because I am a little afraid of the big China
因為我有一點很怕很大的中國
Anyway, everything I think about you
反正我對你的一切想法
Anyway, starting from my own strength
就反正是從我自己的力氣出發
basically like this
基本上是這樣
you go ahead and have a problem
你再往前有一個問題
Sorry because there seem to be four or five questions
對不起,因為好像有四五個問題
That is the Kuomintang and the Democratic Progressive Party
那個就是國民黨跟民進黨
They each said not to rush away
他們各自說不要急走
become leftist or rightist
變成左派或右派
is to become leftists and rightists
就是變成左派跟右派
knowledge all together
知識什麼的都在一起
It’s just a party, it has leftist ideas and rightist ideas
就是一個黨它又會有左派的想法跟右派的想法
Co-exist
共同存在
not easy
不容易啦
Because these two are not in the party
因為這兩個不在黨裡頭
It is usually said that we engage in luxury tax
平常說我們搞奢侈稅
Its rightists always have to oppose it
它的右派總是要反對吧
I don't know the reason for these rightists
我不知道這些右派的原因
Maybe it's because of the overlap of ideology
可能是因為意識形態的關疊
Or
或者說
What about the people in the air-conditioned house you drank
你喝了冷氣房屋的人還怎樣
it is broken disapproval
它就是破不贊成
it will have friction on various interests
它就各種各樣的利益會有摩擦
Can such a situation exist in the same party?
那這樣子在同一個黨裡頭是不是能存在
Unless your party happens to be just below the middle level
除非你這個黨剛好就差在中級
The distance between your left and right is actually not very far from each other
你這左跟右其實彼此的距離差得不很遠
that would be possible
那會有可能
but my opinion is
可是我的看法是
if the economy is bad
如果經濟不好的話
It means that the economic endowment becomes smaller
就表示經濟的稟變小
When the economic endowment becomes smaller
當經濟稟變小的時候
share that talent
分那個稟
The truth and the conflict become bigger
那個真實跟衝突就變大
The left and right cutting methods are different
那左跟右的切法分法不一樣
very difficult
都很困難
I want this party to split into two parties
要的是這個黨split變成兩個黨
What is needed is that the party has a relatively large force
要的是這個黨有比較大的力量
eat that little power
把那個小的力量吃住
then take it aside
然後把它往一邊帶
it's more likely
這是比較可能的
Because I haven't seen in any example
因為我還沒有看到在什麼例子裡頭
Horizontal left and horizontal right will appear in the middle of a party
橫左跟橫右會在一個黨中間出現
I'm afraid it's not easy
恐怕不容易
Because it still has to maintain a party
因為它還是要維持一個黨
still have a question
還有一個問題
good
好
Hello Mr. Wu
吳老師你好
In fact, the problem is a bit similar to the one just now.
其實有問題跟剛剛那個有點像
And I'm curious too
而且我也蠻好奇就是說
Did you just mention that there are two axes?
你剛剛提到有兩個軸線嘛
We all know this axis.
認同這個軸線我們都很清楚嘛
but as a scholar
但是作為一個學者
I don't know if you went
我不曉得說你有沒有去
some thoughts
一些想法
That’s how we get to the major economy file
就是我們怎麼去major經濟這個檔案
because it sounds like
因為聽起來
we can probably accept saying
我們大概可以接受說
economy is an important issue
經濟是一個重要的議題
but you are the last
可是你最後最後
You said something in your tappa game
你的台帕的局裡面你說了點
We use left and right to divide
我們是用左右去分
In fact, we don't go left and right.
其實我們也不是用左右去
Alignment with our political party or political competition
跟我們政黨或政治競爭的走線
It sounds like we are currently or the economy is on this line
聽起來我們目前或是說經濟在這個走線上面
Much depends on our economic relationship with China
很大一個程度是取決於我們跟中國的經濟關係
Including your example of using the EC method is also taking such an example
包括你用EC法例子也是在取這樣一個例子
so i was wondering if you had some ideas
所以我在想說是不是你有一些想法
That is to say, in the case of economics, the face-to-face inquiry is actually
就是說在經濟這個檔面詢上面其實
Maybe it's not about the competition
也許競爭的並不是左右
but one that is highly associated with identity
而是一個跟認同高度相關
Or a direction unrelated to identity
或是說跟認同不相關的一個方向
Thanks
謝謝
If we say that the economic route is the same as the recognized route
如果說經濟的走線跟認同的走線
it should have been mainland words
它應該已經內地的話
of course something went wrong
當然就出問題了
Because I think a question asked by emerging TTS
因為我覺得新興的TTS問的一個問題
it only has one
它只有一個吧
That is, it wants to ask you about the economy
就是它要問你在經濟上面
Do you think the government should
是不是覺得政府應該
it has a
它有一個
its problem
它的問題
Um
嗯
it will
它是會
Advocating that the government should promote social welfare economically is to use ten to express
主張政府應該經濟的推展社會福利是利用十表示
Excuse me, are you closer?
請問你比較靠近啦
on this subject
就這一題
I think Wu Minnie is here
我就覺得吳美妮到了
As far as Wu Minxi is concerned
就吳美妮西方的話
Her lecture seat is very suitable
她那個講座位是非常適及的
so she should make a
所以她應該要做一個
One is social welfare in Hong Kong
一個是在香港的社會福利
One is very appropriate
一個是非常適及的啦
We probably only have this problem
我們大概就只有這種題
In addition, other topics are not distinguished
另外其他題目還分不大出來
So basically you can use this question
所以基本上是可以用這一題
come get your
來把你的
Mark the left and right items
左右的項度給它標出來
0 to 10?
0到10嘛
On the other side, this cultural machine has
另外一邊這個文化機有了
So it can be used like this
所以用這樣是可以用出來
special representation of this space
這個空間的special representation
like that
像那個
is the 2011 president of the American Political Science Association.
就是2011年美國政治學會的會長
at his presidential address
在他的presidential address
specifically mentioned this
就專門有提到這個
The axis they thought was still just right
他們以為的軸線還是剛好
7 minutes left and right
左右7分
But he has now switched to speaking from your point of view
但是他現在已經轉成從你的角度來講
and like this
並這樣子了
It turned out that he came out with a social conservatism
原來是因為他出了一個社會保守主義
Then his horizontal axis is the household income
然後他的橫軸就是那個家戶所得
he is not around
他還不是左右
he is household income
他是用家戶所得
The horizontal axis is more interesting
橫軸更有趣了
how often does he go to church
他是用多久上一次教堂
This is to show your conservatism and your profit
這個來表示你的保守性跟你們的利貨
Then he found out that household income if so
然後他發現家戶所得如果是這樣
words from your point of view
從你的角度來看的話
is so
是這樣
Is that right?
這樣對不對
Then the higher you go, the more conservative you are
然後越往上的話是越保守
The lower you go, the more liberal you are
越往下的話是越自由派
The farther to this side, the lower the income
越這一邊的話是所得越低
The more you go to this side, the higher your income
越這一邊的話是所得越高
so the democrats are here
所以民主黨就在這裡
And the Republican Party is here
而共和黨就在這裡
His axis is cut like this
他的軸線是這樣切下來
so you don't ask me what i mean
這樣你不要問我的意思
So it is possible to use something like
所以可以用那樣的東西
Senior Wu
吳學長
In education or in Wu Xuechang
在教育還是在吳學長
please teach me
請教一下
Between identity and economy are two different gates
認同跟經濟中間是兩個檔門訊
Looks like it's depoliticized
看起來好像是去除政治
There are still some deficiencies
還有一些不足的地方
Just a continuation of his previous question
就是延續他剛的問題
Economy is still a main axis Life
經濟還是一個主軸 生活
actually agreeing here
實際上在認同這邊
it's just that we separate it
只是我們把它區隔
for two opposites
是為了兩個對立
So called separate
所以叫separate
You can use the opposition between the upper class and the lower class
你可以用上層社會跟下層社會的對立
or we use the opposite of identity
或是我們用認同的對立
just a matter of sampling
只是一個取樣的問題
practical economic problems
實際上經濟的問題
We can see from the trend of the world
我們可以看到從世界的趨勢來看
American welfare
美國的福利
then go to democracy
然後走民主
This slowly walks inside a dead activity
這慢慢走到一個死活動裡面
it's already the world is flat
它已經世界是平的
it has no advantage
它也沒什麼優勢
Then oil, war, weapons, stuff like that
然後石油 戰爭 武器這一類東西
In fact it has no advantage
實際上它的優勢沒有
but currently it looks like
但是目前看起來
China Korea and Singapore
中國 韓國跟新加坡
It is the dominant power of the whole country
它整個國家在主導的力量
On the contrary, compared with this democratic progressive way
反而比這種民主的進步的方式
Productivity is more efficient
生產力 效率還更高
so these few
所以這幾個
So from this point of view, for example, the two opposites of democracy
所以從這個比如說民主兩個對立
The two opposing identities of Taiwan
後面台灣的兩個對立認同
In fact, there are two hands behind
後面其實後面還有兩隻手
One is the hands of the CCP and the hands of the United States
一個是中共的手跟美國的手
Because in the early years we got our economy from the United States
因為早年我們是從美國這邊取得經濟
Benefit Oyen got a lot of orders
利益歐伊恩拿到很多訂單
Like which side of China is the same?
像中國這邊有哪邊是一樣
It will give us quite a lot of benefits
它這邊會給我們蠻多的利益
So it's also called what counts for us
所以它也是叫做給我們算什麼
What's the benefit?
什麼給利嘛
It is also to give us some favor
它也是要給我們一些favor
so wrestling in the back
所以在後面的角力
It's because of the shadow behind that hand
是因為後面的影子那隻手
The CCP and the United States are actually behind the hand
中共跟美國其實後面那隻手在後面
behind two parties
兩個政黨後面
still have this hand in it
還是有這個手在裡面
Interfering with Taiwan operations between us
干擾我們的之間的台灣運作
So Taiwan is a
所以台灣是一個
under the big gear
大齒輪下面
middle pinion
角力中間的小齒輪
So when it comes to Taiwan's identity and economy
所以在談到台灣的認同跟經濟
Recognition is just a marketing position
認同只是一個marketing的position
That is to say, to position you and go there
就是說定位你走那個
there must be opposition
一定有反對力量
This factor actually depends on some other
這個因素其實還要參照一些其他的
Does factor come in to see politics more?
factor進來會不會比較看政治
Taiwan's trend will be clearer
台灣的走勢會比較更清楚一點
I agree with this thing
我同意認同這個東西
Originally it was an emotional attachment
本來它是一個情緒附著
economy is important
經濟重要是很重要
not just think about it
不只近想想看
It is also an emotional attachment to the economy
對於經濟也是一個情緒附著
but you can say
但你可以講說
not like that
不是那樣子
real life needs
現實生活必然需要
doomed in gestalt
完形中注定
but real life
可是現實生活
whatever is good
就怎樣才是好
how totally unacceptable
怎樣是完全不可接受
I heard that I am happy not to be in charge
我聽說不擔任很快樂
that is
就是說
its living income
它的生活所得
Morality may be quite low
口德可能蠻低
but its expectations may not be high
但是它的期待可能不高
So many people are full of the psychological aspect
所以很多人都滿心理的那個面向
Then you just mentioned that
那你剛剛這個提到說
Identity is more illusory
認同比較虛幻
Then the economy is a more practical thing
那麼經濟是比較實際的東西
i agree
我同意說
these two things
這兩個東西
in particular
特別是
not so strong identity distinction
不是那麼強的認同區別
When comparing with economic
跟經濟在做比較的時候
possible economic
可能經濟會
overwhelm this recognition
會壓過這個認同
I think Taiwan
我覺得這邊台灣
It's kind of like this situation
就有點像是這樣一個情形
Many of the countries mentioned are like Dongdong
提到的很多比方東東的國家
many places
好多地方
But I really can't see it at all
可是真的完全看不出來
a bit of economic logic there
一點經濟邏輯在那裡
It's that different race
就是它那個不同種族
between different village schools
不同的村校之間
deep hatred
深層的仇恨
So it got to the point where
所以到了那樣的一個地步
it's really hard to draw
它真的是好難畫的
Even if the north shore is the same as the south
即使北岸而南都是一樣
So I think it might depend on the place
所以我覺得可能要看地方
But there is no such thing in Taipei anymore
但台北已經沒有那樣一個東西存在
you just said
那剛剛你講說
Is there a hand outside?
是不是外面有手
of course
當然是
Then it manipulates
然後它這個操縱
of course we manipulate
我們當然會操縱
but manipulator
不過操縱也者
nor can it decide
它也不能夠決定
what will the ending be
結局會是什麼樣
Let me give another example
我再舉個例子來講好
You see the United States is so powerful
你看美國那麼的強大
The overlord of the world ran to fight
全世界的霸主跑去打
It's the sinful Afghanistan.
就孽厚的阿富汗打了
13 years of fighting
大打13年嗎
Yes or no
是不是
Right, how about it? It will push the Tulian to withdraw its troops. It may not be possible to deal with him.
對的怎麼樣 會推徒聯要撤軍 搞不定他
What do you say about the physical, cultural, military, and political power that you want to stop?
你說這個欲罷的 物質的 文化的 軍事的 政治的力量
Guardianship of the poorest circle
對最貧窮厄厚的這塊圓的監護性
He has nothing to do with him
他拿他一點辦法都沒有
So the power of diplomacy is to influence Taiwan
所以外交的力量是在影響台灣
But the way he influences results
但是他影響的方法 結果
It may also be beyond the power of diplomacy to conceive
也可能不是外交的力量所能夠想像的
Another point is that no one likes to be manipulated.
還有一點 就是大家都不喜歡被操縱
So if you take us to the crossbar, who is very clearly manipulating us?
所以你帶我們橫桿就要 誰在非常清楚的操縱我們的話
he may have a distaste will come out
他可能會有一個反感會出來
Because antipathy could also turn into an election
因為反感也可能就變成一個選舉
a very important factor
裡頭一個很重要的因素
What you said is what I agree with, on a large scale
你講的就是 我都贊成 大規模上都贊成
But when the actual sexual desire has an impact, it depends on the situation.
但實際性慾的產生影響的時候 就要看情形
What impact will it have when
在什麼時候會產生什麼影響
He knew it very well Zhu Wenqing
他就很清楚的 朱文青
once before the taiwan election
曾經在台灣選舉之前
I'll let you guys feel that you can't do anything wrong.
就讓你們這個做覺得不要做錯啦這樣
As a result, after you talked about this
結果這東西你講到來了以後
Elections in Taiwan
對於台灣的選舉
The child did not achieve what he wanted
小孩沒有達到他所要的效果
so
這樣
Hello, teacher
老師你好
Excuse me, just ask
不好意思 請問一下就是
In the process of transaction reform
在交易改革的過程裡面
There are so-called multi-entry water and multiple copies in one tank
有所謂的多元入水跟一缸多本
Is that a multi-cylinder?
那一缸多本是不是
It is this history and luck
就是這個歷史跟運化的
A prohibition on the question of identity
認同的問題的一個禁止
That is to say
也就是說
When the Democrats were in power
在民進黨執政的時候
This syllabus is
這個課綱就是
bully sinicization
欺中國化
When the Democratic Party was in power
在國民黨執政的時候
It's just bullying Taiwan
就是欺台灣化
If you are a general recruit of a course
如果你是一個課綱的總招
History or Chinese Yunhua
歷史或者是中國運化
General tricks in Chinese English
中國英文的總招
or a trade worker
或者是一個交易工作者
then you should be
那你應該是
how to take responsibility
怎麼來接責
Or just pay attention when students take exams
或者只是注意學生考試的時候
How much Gao Wen can take an exam?
能夠考多少高文
Can go to star high school or star university
能夠到明星高中或者明星大學
You will pay more attention to that impression
你會比較注意那一個印象
then you will have a hard time answering
那你會好難答
because you are a teacher
因為你是老師
this is no way
這就是沒辦法
His syllabus determines
他的課綱決定了
Textbook decided
課本決定了
Then the exam is like that
然後考試是那樣的格局
Of course you let your students
你當然是讓你的學生
able to do well
能夠考得好
So in that situation
所以那個情境底下
how to get him out
怎麼樣讓他搭出
The standard answer that is considered correct
那個被認為正確的標準答案
you can't say easily
你不能不容易說
The classmate's current textbook has changed
同學現在的課本改了
but the current direction
但是現在的方向
so you make us
所以你使我們
For this reason
因為這個原因
considered wrong
被認為是錯的
We still have to choose D
我們還是要選擇D
instead of choosing A
而不可以選擇A
it's hard
這很難
then you talk about that
那你講那個
In the beginning this and that decision
一開始這個那個決定
What should be the curriculum
對於課綱究竟應該怎麼樣
that stuff is more difficult
那個東西就更困難
why is it difficult
為什麼困難
because it's ingrained
因為這是根深蒂固的
values ​​and beliefs
價值跟信仰
see many historians
看到很多歷史學者
The view of each other is south far north side
彼此之間的看法是南遠北側的
have heard their editorials on many occasions
有很多場合聽過他們的編論
some people think
有人會覺得
Taiwan is a Chinese nation
台灣就是一個中華民族
like the one in this extension
像在這個擴展的一個
one this
一個這個
how to say
怎麼講
one
一個
a river street
一個江街
a pioneering region
一個開拓的地區
So here's the
所以這裡展現的
all this
都是這個
This traditional Chinese culture
這個傳統的中華文化
then in this
然後是在這個
Under this special situation
這個特別的情境底下
Then this displayed
然後這個所展現出來的
i really thought you understood
我真的以為你去理解
Some people don't see it that way at all
有人根本完全不是這樣子看
Then he imagined himself
然後他對於自己的想像
Follow the influence from mainland China
跟對從中國大陸來的影響
or something
或者是什麼
is highly repulsive
是很高度的排斥的
because how do you go
因為你如何去
I got it
我知道啦
Actually now
其實現在
what actually happened
就實際的狀況發生的是什麼呢
The Democratic Progressive Party will say that scholars who have a little more access to the road will go in
民進黨會講多塞一點路的學者進去
The KMT will try to squeeze more scholars into it
國民黨會想多塞一點來的學者進去
Some people are tighter
有的人塞得比較兇
Some people are more skillful
有的人塞得比較技巧
Some people are not strong enough
有的人塞得比較不夠力
and how to get the final syllabus
還有如何最後得出來的課綱
A Political Compromise
一個Political Compromise
this is what actually happened
這是實際發生的情形
It is actually reflected in Taiwan's own
它其實反映在台灣本身對於
The confrontation of many values
很多價值觀點看法的對峙
Just like the stone hills in the mainland I just mentioned
就像我剛剛講的大陸石崗
stone hill
跟海洋的石崗
Mathematics and Mathematics
數源主義跟數地主義
talk about interests
要講利益
Each of these can tell something
這都各自可以講出一些
But it doesn't really matter there
但那裡其實根本也都不重要
when speaking
講的時候
Does it touch my heart
是不是打動我心
As for whether it touches my heart
至於是不是打動我的心
It depends on my growing environment
是看我的生長環境
background family etc.
背景 家庭等等
are directly linked
是直接聯繫在一起的
i find it difficult
我覺得很難
this thing to comment
這個東西去做評論
But the syllabus is set, the textbook is set
但是課綱定了 課本定了
people who read the syllabus
讀課綱 讀課本的人
will have a certain opinion
會有一定的看法
this is yes
這個是的
No wonder both sides want
難怪雙方就想要
scramble so fast
爭奪這麼快的
Dominance?
主導權嗎
OK
好的
we are only for a minute
我們只是一分鐘
So our young friend from earlier
所以我們剛才那位年輕朋友
I'm asking for advice after the meeting
會後在請教
i said a few words before
我說幾句話前
Director Wu gave a very brilliant speech today
這個吳所長今天非常精采的演講
But his answer is still on the ground
但是他的答案還在落地
It's just that political scientists are different from my historians.
就是政治學者跟我歷史學者不一樣
once i was at a dinner party
有一次我參加一個晚宴
anxious to go home
急著要回家
Japan finds Tian University's vice president
日本找到田大學的副校長
say anything
什麼都說
what are you doing in such a hurry
你這麼急幹什麼
Will it still be common?
其實還會普遍嗎
tends to be a nice guy
往往會變一個好人嗎
not later
不會晚一點
text is writing the same
文字在寫一樣
But politics is different
可是政治學不一樣
Political science will not be the same the day after tomorrow
政治學明天的後天還不一樣
Look at Director Wu's topic today
你看吳所長今天的題目
left for us
給我們留下來的
Tomorrow and the day after tomorrow, the Democratic Progressive Party of the Jiangnan Kuomintang
明天後天江南國民黨的民進黨
what has become
還變成什麼樣
Still uncustomized
還在未定制天
still developing
還在一直發展
leave us with a question to think about
留給我們一個思考的問題
a thinking difficulty
一個思考的困難
Thank you for his wonderful speech today
謝謝他今天精采的演講
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you.
Thank you.